<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The judgment of urines. By Robert Record Doctor of Physick Whereunto is added an ingenious treatise concerning physicians, apothecaries, and chirurgeons, set forth by an eminent physitian in Queen Elizabeths dayes. With a translation of Papius Ahalsossa concerning apothecaries confecting their medicines; worthy perusing, and imitating.</title>
            <author>Record, Robert, 1510?-1558.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R650A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220684</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832080</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832080</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36549</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36549)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2055:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The judgment of urines. By Robert Record Doctor of Physick Whereunto is added an ingenious treatise concerning physicians, apothecaries, and chirurgeons, set forth by an eminent physitian in Queen Elizabeths dayes. With a translation of Papius Ahalsossa concerning apothecaries confecting their medicines; worthy perusing, and imitating.</title>
                  <author>Record, Robert, 1510?-1558.</author>
                  <author>Pape, Joseph, 1558-1622. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 111, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by Peter Parker at the Leg and Star in Cornhil; against the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A translation of Papius concerning apothecaries" is a translation of Pape's Tractatus de medicamentorum praeparationibus; published in Wittenberg in 1612.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; stained and tightly bound with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Sion College Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Urine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE JUDGMENT OF <hi>Vrines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Record</hi> Doctor of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added an ingenious Treatiſe concerning <hi>Phyſicians, Apothecaries,</hi> and <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> Set forth by an Eminent Phyſitian in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes.</p>
            <p>With a Tranſlation of <hi>Papius Ahal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſſa</hi> concerning <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting their Medicines; Worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing, and imitating.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Peter Parker</hi> at the <hi>Leg</hi> and <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F either the corruption, or abuſe of things, might deprive us of this lawfull and neceſſary uſe of them, even the ſacred Scriptures, our laws, our proviſions of life and clothing, might fall under declenſion, if not abolition: It is true from the inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Urine, ſome have preſumed to pretend a larger judgement, and indication, then may juſtly be drawn or conjectured out of it; yet it is generally concluded by Phyſitians,
<pb facs="tcp:36549:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
both ancient and moderne, that both Urine and Pulſe are ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that without them all knowledge of Phyſick, beſides, is doubtfull, obſcure, and uncertaine: whereof the firſt ſheweth the eſtate of the liver and veines, the ſecond of the heart and arteries: The Urine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with the blood it is conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed into all parts of the body, and from thence returneth back again in the veines, to the liver and urinall veſſels, bringeth with it ſome indicature of the ſtate and diſpoſition of all thoſe parts from whence it commeth: and who ſhall pleaſe to peruſe that exact peice of <hi>Daniel Becherus,</hi> ſhall finde obſervable peices, both concerning the urine, and divers experimented medicines made with it. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the judgement of the Pulſe, who ſhall pleaſe to peruſe Doctor
<pb facs="tcp:36549:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>May</hi> upon <hi>Pennant,</hi> ſhall finde the Pulſes motion not ſo certain an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, becauſe in ſome diſeaſes there is ceſſation, or none, or ſmall appearance to conjecture by. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Author, he was one of the firſt who labour'd to reduce the tractate thereof, unto order and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and hath been ſeconded by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious <hi>Fletcher,</hi> to whom our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Nation oweth much for their labours: The antiquity and paines of the Author hath cauſed it to be preſented again to the Preſſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, with judicious men, it ſhall receive the acceptance is deſired and ſtudied</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By the well-wiſher of your health,</hi> R. R.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:5"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The good uſe of a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the unſatiable greedines of covetous men doe many and ſundrie waies hurt, yet ſome wayes it may do no leſſe good, if men will not diſdain (as they ought not) to uſe it in ſuch ſort as I ſhall ſhew you.</p>
            <p>But becauſe that unſaciableneſs is never ſatisfied, but beſide thouſand of means in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented already to quench the unquenchable greedines, it ſeeketh and findeth daily new and new means innumerable, ſo that it were an infinite labour to declare them all. I will wittingly, and purpoſedly paſſe them over, only taking one general ſentence, which ſhall be in ſtead of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> one of the great ſchoolmaſters of avarice, which could pick out profit of every thing (yea, even of mens urine) taught his Scholers (I meane the whole court of covetous perſons) this leſſon enſuing:
<q>
                  <l>Lucri bonus odor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> qualibet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36549:6"/>Lucre is ſweet, and hath a good ſavour;</l>
                  <l>Though it come of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, dirt or Ordure.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This ſentence, if it be withdrawn from the filthy lucre of unſatiable covetouſneſſe, wherein it is deteſtable, and imployed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the due lucre of mans ſuſtenance, then it becomes tolerable: But if it bee referred to the neceſſarie lucre of mans health, then is it greatly commendable. If there can be then any commodity for mans health gathered out of urine, (as there may be much) men ſhould not be negligent in ſeeking of that thing which ſhould do good both to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others? ſeeing the covetous are ſo diligent in ſeeking for that thing which ſhall profit neither themſelves nor others?</p>
            <p>And the negligence is ſo much the greater, if men be more remiſſe in ſeeking after ſo neceſſary a thing in a matter ſo commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then the covetous in a bad thing.</p>
            <p>But in as much as this thing (by reaſon it is not plainly ſet forth) is with no leſſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to be ſtudied on, then it is neceſſary to be uſed, the ignorant may have ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe: I therefore in the name of many other, have taken this pains on me, to ſet forth this thing ſo plainly,<note place="margin">Ignorance ſet aſide.</note> that ignorance can have no excuſe.</p>
            <p>But that no man ſhould doubt of the truth
<pb facs="tcp:36549:6"/>
of this Treatiſe, or of mine intent,<note place="margin">Why this Book is written.</note> in putting forth the ſame rather in this our Engliſh tongue then any other: I ſhall briefly ſhew reaſons of both; Firſt, for the truth of it,<note place="margin">The firſt reaſon.</note> I will boldly ſpeak, knowing for certain that no man that can judge it, will ſay or thinke otherwiſe, but that it is as true as mans knowledge can deviſe it. And it is the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the moſt excellent writers of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick both Greeks and Latine; namely, <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates, Galen, Aetius, Aegin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus, Theophilus, Actuarius:</hi> alſo <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Celſus Plinius, Conſtantinus, Africa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Clementius Clementinus,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers more, conferring alſo with theſe <hi>Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenna, Egidius, Polidamus,</hi> and ſuch like: But with what temperance and moderation they that are learned may perceive. Theſe have I followed chiefly in this judgement of Urines.</p>
            <p>And in the uſe of medicine and diſeaſes touching urine, I have joyned with them <hi>Dioſcorides, Quintus Serenus, Columela, Sextus Platonicus,</hi> and divers others. Now if there be any man that doubteth of the truth of thoſe writers in this thing, I am not here to force beleef upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The inter of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</note>But now as touching mine intent in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Treatiſe in Engliſh; though this
<pb facs="tcp:36549:7"/>
cauſe might ſeem ſufficient to ſatisfie many men, that I am an Engliſh man, and therefore may moſt eaſily and plainly write in my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive tongue, rather then in any other: yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that know the hardneſs of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, this anſwer ſhould ſeem unlikely: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that it is harder to tranſlate into ſuch a tongue, wherein the Art hath not been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before, then to write in thoſe tongues in which the terms of the Art are better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
            <p>Now to ſhew briefly the cauſes moving me thereunto. I am ſure, there are but few that ever ſought counſell for their health, but they know that the common trade to attain to the knowledge of the diſeaſe, is by the judgement of the urine, though not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, yet as the principall.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, as there is not any thing ſo good, but the abuſe of it may cauſe harm to enſue therupon. So this judgment of urines, though it be a thing highly to be regarded, yet if it be uſed raſhly without foregoing ſigns it may cauſe (as it doth often) ſome error in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Phyſitian, though he were right excellently learned: not ſo much by the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Phyſitian, as by want of knowledge in the patient, which ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Phyſitian, in ſuch queſtions as hee
<pb facs="tcp:36549:7"/>
needed to demand of him: and not to look that the Phyſitian ſhould tell him all things at the firſt ſight, more like a God then man.</p>
            <p>So that if there be any Phyſitian ſo arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, that he will take upon him to tell all things alone, and will not hear the Patient ſpeak, ſpecially not knowing the party be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, neither ſeeing other ſignes but only the urine, as I dare boldly pronounce, That ſuch a man is unworthy to be called a Phyſitian. So it ſhall be good for all men, not to truſt to the judgement of ſuch a one: for by ſuch miſ-uſe in this thing not only much harme befalls the patients, ſo that it hath been the occaſion of many mens death, but alſo very much reproach hath enſued to the whole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and order of Phyſitians, and hath cauſed that excellent and moſt neceſſary art to bee contemned, derided, and little ſet by.</p>
            <p>To avoid the more this inconvenience, I have written this little Treatiſe to all men in common,<note place="margin">The uſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Book.</note> that they may learn to have ſome knowledge in their own urines, and thereby may be the better able to inſtruct the Phyſitian, at the leaſt, what ſort of urine they have made from time to time from the beginning of their ſicknes, and ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And alſo what ſort of water they were
<pb facs="tcp:36549:8"/>
wont to make in their health? ſo that if men will be diligent to mark their water in time of health, they ſhall not only be able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Phyſitian (as I have ſaid) but ſhould bee alſo able to perceive the cauſe of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſometimes before the grief come, and ſo by the counſell of ſome diſcreet Phyſitian avoid the ſicknes before it bee fully entred: yea, and by due marking of their urine, they ſhall perceive from time to time, how they ſhall governe themſelves in meats and drinks, in exerciſe and reſt, and the like things, ſo that thereby they may eſchew both the diſeaſes, and alſo the cauſes of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now what a commodity this may bee to all men, and what thanks he hath deſerved that hath taught this ſo great a commodity to all men in generall, I leave it to every mans own judgement.</p>
            <p>And thus (as you may perceive) I have declared the cauſes of this my pains, taking them to be for the profit of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons indifferently. Howbeit, if any mean learned Phyſitian ſhall be thereby furthered in his judgement, I will not envie him, but will be the gladder, the more number of men I perceive to take benefit by it.</p>
            <p>I am ſure that the true judgement of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines,
<pb facs="tcp:36549:8"/>
according to the mind of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of Judgemen in Urine.</note> 
               <hi>Galen,</hi> and ſuch like, is very hard, though not to excellent Clerks, yet to the meaner ſort; partly by reaſon that it is written ſo diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly in their works, and not in any one Book peculiarly and ſufficiently: and partly becauſe that ſundry words uſed in the ſame (as in the reſt of Phyſick) are obſcure to them that have not been exerciſed in all kinds of learning, and that with the knowledge of both the Greek and Latine tongues. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I truſt, that this my pains ſhall be ſome help alſo, to them that lack the exerciſe of ſuch ſtudie and knowledge.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there is a common ſaying in the mouths of many men now a dayes, that it is a profaining of learning, and a meanes to bring it into contempt, ſo to ſet it forth in the vulgar tongue, that every man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently may read it, and ſtudy it:<note place="margin">The anſwer unto it.</note> To this I will briefly anſwer, that this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is not onely againſt many great learned mens acts and examples, but alſo againſt manifeſt reaſons: beſides, that it encludeth a pernitious kinde of counſell. For if every thing ſhould be put away, or left undone, that evill men may pervert and uſe to an evill purpoſe, ſo ſhould we have no good thing remain: meats and drinks muſt be
<pb facs="tcp:36549:9"/>
taken away, becauſe many abuſe of it. And becauſe evill men doe abuſe of both eyes, and tongues, ſhall all men therefore pluck out their eyes and their tongues? Becauſe many men doe abuſe lawes and authority, ſhall men expell lawes and high powers? Many evill men and hereticks have miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted Gods word, yet ought Gods word nevertheleſſe to be taught vulgarly to all men. Though the Pope, Cardinals, and Monkes, have practiſed to poyſon men, even with the very Sacrament of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord, yet no man will be ſo mad, therefore to eſchue the uſe of that bleſſed Sacrament: And yet all this followeth, if men allow that common ſaying, above writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Better meanes it were to ſet forth pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly all that might doe good to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique wealth, and ſtreightly to puniſh the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes of them, then to puniſh good men and good things, becauſe that evill men offend. It is a like error to that ſort of doctrine, which contemned wine as an evill thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that many were made drunken with it. But to leave this, and to come more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the matter.</p>
            <p>What is learning unlearned, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge unknown, any thing elſe but a vaine name? Learning then encreaſeth moſt, when
<pb facs="tcp:36549:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it is ſtudied of moſt: And learning then triumpheth moſt, when it hath moſt favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and followers. And then doth igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (learnings enemy) rejoyce moſt, when learning reigneth in feweſt, and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ruleth moſt: ſo that then is learning moſt profained, contemned, and hated, when it hath moſt enemies: that is to ſay, when moſt men are ignorant. For that old ſaying ſhall alwayes be true: Learning hath no enemy, but the ignorant.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> his ſentence.</note>Aske that great Cleark <hi>Plutarch</hi> what his minde is in this: Whether the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of health be a meet thing for every man to ſtudy: and thou ſhalt heare him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: that ſhame it is for men to obſerve the crying of Crowes, and ſuch like things in beaſts and birds, whereby men judge of the change of weathers, and to be negligent in marking motions within themſelves, and alterations preparing unto ſicknes. Yea he requireth ſo exact knowledge in every man appertaining unto health, that he noteth it for a great ſhame, and calleth it unſenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a man if he be ſo ignorant, that he ſhal need to ask of the Phyſitians, what meats are beſt for him. And to ask what meates ſhall beſt digeſt in him, is as abſurd a queſtion (ſaith he) as to ask what meats are ſweet,
<pb facs="tcp:36549:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſoure, or bitter, and ſuch like. Yea beyon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all this, he requireth in every man the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his own pulſe, which is a thing har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then the judgement of urines.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Examples of Writers in the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tongue.</note>Now if you require Examples, the whole world is full of them. They that wrote i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Greek, wrote in their own vulgar tongue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſo did they that wrote in Latine, write<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in their own common ſpeech.</p>
            <p>Beſides that, have we not infinite exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Learned men in <hi>Germany, France,</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> which wrote of Phyſick in their own tongue? Yea, Is not our own <hi>England</hi> full of Examples? How many Books of Practiſes? how many Herbals? and other like Books of Phyſick, hath there been put forth many yeers paſt? And yet unto this day doe not learned wits ſleepe. How much is all <hi>England</hi> bound to that Worthy and Learned Knight Sir <hi>Thomas Eliot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Thomas Eliots</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Health.</note> which took the pains to build a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Health for all Engliſh men (beſides many other learned Books that he hath pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forth in the Vulgar tongue) whereby a man may learn both to govern himſelf ſo, that though he eſcape not all ſickneſſes quite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet he ſhall eſchew the great dangers of them? <hi>England</hi> may rejoyce of ſuch a Knight: yea, <hi>England</hi> hath too few that
<pb facs="tcp:36549:10"/>
followeth ſuch example. But if <hi>England</hi> had as many well willing doers as ſhe hath cruell and ſpitefull diſdainers, then were <hi>England</hi> the Flower of all Realmes in the world.</p>
            <p>Now will I leave this and draw nearer to my purpoſe, and will deſire all men that ſhall read this Book, patiently to bear with my boldneſs, and thankfully to receive my good minde. And if there ſhall bee found in this Book, or in any other that I ſhall put forth, a ſmall error or overſight (for greater errors, I dare ſay there ſhall be none) I ſhall deſire all them that ſhall find any, to advertiſe me thereof by word or writing, and I ſhall be ready not onely to render condign thanks, but alſo to amend duely that ſhall be thought amiſſe, or elſe to yeeld a reaſon for the proof of the ſame,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Reader.</note>And now to make an end: I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire every man ſoberly and diſcreetly to uſe this my Book, not uſing it to the taunting or checking of other men: nor to truſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir own knowledge further then they ought.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe I ſhall exhort all men, not to mock and jeſt with any Phyſitian (as ſome light wits do) tempting them with
<pb facs="tcp:36549:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Beaſts ſtale, in ſtead of mens urine: others bringing to them mens water for womens, and ſuch other like things. For in this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they deceive not the Phyſitian, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For a mans water to be like a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, it need ſeem no ſtrange thing. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, again there is a notable difference, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that that water which in a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth health, if it were a womans, might declare ſome diſeaſe; and likewiſe that which in a woman ſignifieth health, if it were a mans water, it might betoken ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And if a mans water and womans be like, and betoken both diſeaſes, thoſe diſeaſes may be divers and not one.</p>
            <p>Yea two mens waters being both alike, ſhall not declare alwaies one grief, except they agree alſo in age, diet, exerciſe, and other like things</p>
            <p>Alſo, that a Beaſts Water may be like a Mans (the Mans ſickneſſe being thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) <hi>Hypocrates</hi> witneſſeth, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth, as I ſhall declare hereafter.</p>
            <p>Therefore if you ſeek the Patients health, look that you receive the urine diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and as ſoon as you can, preſent it to the Phyſitian, and be diligent to inſtruct him in all things that you can, and that
<pb facs="tcp:36549:11"/>
he ſhall not have need to aske. And ſo no doubt, you ſhall receive great commodity of that Art, to the health of man, and the glory of God, which hath given ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge unto man.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36549:12"/>
            <head>THE URINALL OF PHYSICK.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Diviſion and Order of this Book.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe that nothing done confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly can be well underſtood of the Readers, for every thing the better order it hath, the better it may be underſtood, and is much more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily remembred, when the order of it is well and certainly known:<note place="margin">The ſum of this Book.</note> I have therefore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted this Book orderly, as I ſhall here ſet forth, to the intent that you may read, as it were in groſſe the whole Book, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by keep it the better in remembrance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36549:13"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, therefore I will declare the nature of urine, what it is, and how it is ingendred within man, and how it paſſeth forth from man.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, of the order of receiving it in a convenient veſſell. And of the time and place meet to conſider it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, how many things are to bee conſidered in urine: and how many wayes they may be altered in a healthfull man.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, what ſignifications and tokens may be gathered of urine, concerning any alteration in man, paſt, preſent, or to come,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, to what uſe in medicine urine may ſerve: and of other good uſes of it to mans commodity.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> And laſt of all, I wil declare certain diſeaſes touching urine, which either let it, or cauſe it to void unwillingly: with the Medicines and remedies meet for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine is ingendred in Man and how it paſſeth forth.</head>
               <p>AS unto them that are learned and know by the Art of Anatomy the ſcituation of the parts of man, and the naturall office
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36549:13"/>
of every part, it is eaſie enough to perceive the originall generation and cauſe of urine, without any example: ſo unto them that neither know the ſcituation, nor offices, no, neither yet the names of the parts of mans body, it is ſcarce poſſible to make them to perceive the generation of urine, without ſome ſenſible example<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> But becauſe it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard to find an artificiall example, which can alone duely expreſſe this work of nature, I will uſe therefore an example of a natural work, which ſhall expreſſe in many points this thing, though not in all; for ſuch can there none be, but the thing it ſelf.</p>
               <p>And in as much as this example is not eaſie to be underſtood of all men, though the moſt part do now a daies partly know it by experience of finding ſprings of waters, I will firſt propoſe an artificiall example, to make both the other to be the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note>It is daily ſeen in diſtilling of Waters, that the temperate heat of the fire doth ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the pureſt part of the juice from the herbs, and alſo from the groſſer juice. This by naturall lightneſs is drawn into the head of the Stillatorie, where by the coldneſs of the helmet, it is made ſomewhat groſſer, and ſo through naturall heat deſcendeth and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36549:14"/>
paſſeth forth by the Pipe of the Stillato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note>And as the Art of man uſeth to make this water, ſo doth nature uſe to make the water of ſprings, whereof come all rivers, ſtreams and floods, except the ſea. For ſeeing the earth is not perfectly ſound and thick of ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Cauſe of ſprings.</note> as ſtones and ſome woods appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be, but it is hollow and full of holes, as you ſee that cork is: ſo that the air which by his ſubtleneſs pierceth into never ſo little a hole, entreth and filleth this hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nature ſo leading to it, becauſe no place ſhould be emptie: In which place by the coldneſs of the earth, the air is turned into water, as you may ſee in walls and pillars of ſtone, namely, of marble, how the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſtone turneth the air into wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and hangeth full of drops, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times trickle down apace, as if they did ſweat. So when the earth hath turned the air thus into water, then doth it drop down and gathereth together, and ſo run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth out as it can finde or prepare way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As long therefore as there is hollownes in that place, with ſuch ſort of coldneſſe, and none other let, the Spring of water ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> never ceaſe. But if the way by any mean be ſtopped, then the water turmoileth and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36549:14"/>
laboureth, either to expell that let, or to make a new way.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The cauſes of diverſity in taſt of Water.</note>Now this water being thus ingendred of the air which hath no taſte, is alſo naturally without all taſte: but the taſt that it hath is the taſte of the vaines of earth or mettall, by which it doth run. And that is the cauſe that ſome waters are ſweet, and ſome ſoure; ſome freſh, and ſome ſalt, and otherwiſe diverſly taſted; ſome alſo are hot, and ſome cold, and with other like qualities endued, according to the ground whereby it paſſeth. But of this I will not now ſpeak, becauſe I have appointed for it a peculiar Treatiſe, if God grant me time: Only this I ſay now, that a man that is expert, can by the colour, taſt, and other qualities of the water which he ſeeth, tell what vains of earth or mettals is in that place whence that water cometh, though he ſee it not.</p>
               <p>And this water is expelled out of his firſt place, as unprofitable there to remain; and yet when it is come forth thence, it is good for divers and ſundry uſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of urine.</note>Thus may we thinke of the generation and uſe of urine or mans water.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions.</note>It ſhall not need that I here reckon exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the places, cauſes, and the order of the three concoctions which go before the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36549:15"/>
of urine, but it ſhall ſuffice to te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> briefly, that of the meat and drink togethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> concocted in the ſtomack is made rud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blood: (if I may ſo call it) which rude bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is wrought again, and made more perfect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the liver: and thirdly yet more purifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in the hollow vein, where the urine i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeparate from it, as whey from milk, but ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may not exactly be called urine, till it com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the reins or kidnies, which draw it ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the hollow vein, by a certain natural power reſting in them. And then doth the reins or kidnies alter it perfectly into urine us the coldnes of the ground turneth air into water. But you muſt take this compariſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſimilitude to be ſpoken of the alteration it ſelf, and not of the cauſe.</p>
               <p>Now when Urine is thus made like to that faſhion of water (as I ſaid) then as the water paſſeth forth from his firſt place, by iſſues outward, ſo doth the urine deſcend from the reins by certain veins (as it were) called Water pipes, and runneth into the bladder, from whence at due times it is expelled forth, if the way be not let. So that you may compare the reins to the head of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit, the water pipes, to the conduit pipes, the bladder to the conduit, and the ſhaft to the rock of the conduit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36549:15"/>And further as the water doth declare by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſte and colour the qualities of the earth, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eins of mettall, whereby it runneth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom whence it commeth, ſo the urine by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olour, and other wayes, declareth of what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort the places that it cometh thorow, and humors that it commeth from are affected.</p>
               <p>And yet not only ſerveth for this, but alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the water, though it depart from the earth as ſuperfluous in that place, yet in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places and to other purpoſes it is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profitable. So the urine, though it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled as a ſuperfluous excrement, yet beſide the commodity of judgement, which it gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth of the parts that it cometh from, it doth alſo ſerve for divers uſes in medicine, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good commodities: Of both which, I will anon orderly write, after I have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red certain things appertaining to the due judgement of it.</p>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36549:16"/>
                  <head>Of the Inſtrument and parts by which <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine is engendred and paſſeth, mark this Figure following.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>excretory system</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Is the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>B.</hi> The hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vein</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>C.</hi> Veins by which the reins do draw the urine, and therefore be called ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing veins.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>D.</hi> The reins.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>E.</hi> The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Pipes.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>F.</hi> Is the Bladder.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>G.</hi> The ſpout of the yard.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All the other parts beſide, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain to Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and ſeed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36549:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> What <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine is, and what tokens it giveth in generall.</head>
               <p>YOu have heard now how urine is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred, from whence it cometh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y what places it paſſeth, which things all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the intent that you may the better keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n minde, you ſhall note this ſhort definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</note>Urine is the ſuperfluity or wheyie ſubſtance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the bloud into a hollow vein, conveyed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he reins and water pipes, into the bladder. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o that hereby you may plainly perceive, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat if the bloud be pure and clean, and none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> grief in the reins, Water-pipes, Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, nor Shaft, then ſhall the urine ſo declare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, being alſo perfect and pure in ſubſtance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd colour, and all other tokens according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the ſame. But if there bee any grief in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny of thoſe parts, or the blood corrupt by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny means, then ſhall the urine declare cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain tokens of the ſame, as I ſhall anon parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ularly expreſſe.</p>
               <p>But firſt it ſhall be neceſſary to inſtruct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou of the veſſel place, and time, meet to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udge urine, and of the manner of receiving</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:36549:17"/>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36549:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36549:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36549:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the form of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinall, and of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and time meet to judge urine, and how it ſhould be received.</head>
               <p>THat urine ſhould be kept to ſee, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is firſt made after midnight common or namely when the patient hath ſlept lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but you muſt take heed whether the pati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be man or woman,<note place="margin">The order to receive urine.</note> that they make not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> urine in another veſſel firſt (as many uſe do) and then pour it into the urinall wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is ſetled, for that cauſeth much de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and error in the judgement of it. And that the Patient cannot well make it in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> urinall, either by weakneſſe, or any ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe, then let them make it in another v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſel; but ſee that it be clean and dry; and ſoon as the water is made, pour it forth p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſently into the Urinall altogether, and lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> no part of it out, as ſome curious folk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſe to put the clear part only into the urin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and caſt away the dregs, as though it ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not with their modeſty to bring ſuch fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gear to the Phyſitian, others of ſuch like fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh mind. Pour it therefore in wholly, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let not the urinall ſtand open, namely in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duſty place, but ſtop it cloſe with a glove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36549:19"/>
other leather, and not with cloth, paper, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay, and let it be brought to the Phyſitian within ſix hours at the furtheſt, for after that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime it cannot well be judged.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Urinal.</note>Now as touching the Urinall, it ſhould be of pure cleer glaſſe, not thick, nor green in colour, without blots or ſpots in it, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at in the bottome, nor too wide in the neck, out wideſt in the midle, and narrow ſtill to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward both the ends, like the faſhion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly of an egg, or of a very bladder being meaſurably blown (for the Vrinall ſhould repreſent the bladder of a man) and ſo ſhall every thing be ſeen in his due place and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. If neither the groſſenes of the Vrinall neither the colour, nor ſpots ſhall let the true ſight of the colour and ſubſtance of the urine, and the contents of it: neither the deform faſhion of the urinall ſhall alter the regions or rooms of the urine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The place</note>Likewiſe concerning the place meet to behold urines, you muſt look that it be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too dark, ſo that your fight ſhould not diſcern perfectly, either the colour, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or contents, for lack of light: neither yet that your ſight be likewiſe deceived, if the place be too light, as in open light or beams of the ſun.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The time.</note>Beſides this alſo you muſt mark the time
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36549:20"/>
due to behold urines, but becauſe there o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no one time be aſſigned certain and exact judge all parts of it, I will briefly ſhew t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> order of the things to be conſidered in the time.</p>
               <p>Firſt, when the urine is made, while it yet ſomewhat hot, you ſhall conſider the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour of it: for that may beſt bee diſcerne then; and likewiſe the thickneſs of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance of it, which if it be mean, ſhall the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be beſt ſeen. All other things, as the bubbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the contents ſhall be beſt judged ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>what after, when the urine is ſomewhat co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and they be duly ſetled in their prope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> How many things are to be conſidered in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
               <p>NOw leaving this as a brief inſtructio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the generation of the Water or U<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rine,<note place="margin">Four things to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in Urine, <hi>viz.</hi> Subſtance, Colour, Quantitie, Contents.</note> and of the manner of receiving it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> veſſels due, with time and place meet to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it. I will particually declare how many things are to be conſidered in it, which ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commonly named four, that is the Subſtance, the Colour, the Quantity, and the Contents
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36549:20"/>
and the Savour thereto may be added as the fift; to the which fift, if you ſhall joyn ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs and order, as two accidents common to the firſt four things, (but yet no leſſe to be conſidered then they) then ſhall you judge the more certainly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Stableneſs.</note>Stablenes is called, when the urine conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth certain daies together of one ſort. And if it alter every day,<note place="margin">Unſtable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Order.</note> then is that called un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtableneſs or changeableneſs, to which thing order doth appertain: For order is the following of one thing after another, as black coloured urine after white, green or pale. I mean not, becauſe that ſo it ought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but only that you muſt obſerve how it doth follow. For black Urine doth not ſignifie the ſame if it follow after green urine, as it doth if it follow after white u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine: ſo that the order ought alſo to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Subſtance.</note>But now to return to the four firſt things.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Three ſorts of ſubſtance in urine. Thin.</note>Subſtance is called in urine, the urine it ſelf, in reſpect of the thickneſs or thinneſs of it: So that there are 3. ſorts of ſubſtance in urine: thick, thin, and mean.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick.</note>Thin ſubſtance is called, when you may perceive well the joynts of your fingers through the urine. And contrariwiſe it is called thick, when you cannot well ſee your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36549:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
fingers through it: and that is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle between extream thick and extream thin,<note place="margin">Mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> is called, mean.</p>
               <p>Colours are divers, but the principall are theſe ſix, white, pale, flaxen, yellow, red and black. And all the other colours are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under theſe ſix.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Light white as Chryſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſnowie.</note>As under white, are contained clear as chryſtal, white as ſnow, and pure as water which three are light whites.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dark white as milke-white, horny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ray, pale, flaxen, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</note>Then are there other three more darker as milk white, cleer like horn, and grey.</p>
               <p>After white, followeth pale colour, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then flaxen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then yellow, which may be called golden, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is the colour of pure gold.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Light ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, ſaffron colour. Claret. Red. Crimſon. Purple. Blew. Green.</note>After it followeth light ſaffron, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaffron, then claret colour, and then red, af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter it crimſon, and then purple, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blue.</p>
               <p>Then is there green of divers kinds, as ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> green, green as graſſe, ſtark green, and dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> green.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Oylie.</note>There are alſo oil colours (that is, popi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gay green) of three ſorts: as of green, ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oily, ſtark oily, and dark oily.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aſh colour.</note>After theſe is there Aſh colour like un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lead;<note place="margin">Black.</note> and after it, as laſt of all cometh blac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And theſe be the chief colours.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:36549:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Now as touching quantity, it is alſo in three ſorts; much, little, and mean.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Quantity Much.</note>Then it is called much quantity, when it exceedeth the meaſure of a mans drinking.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Little.</note>And then is it called little, when a man piſſeth leſſe then he drinketh.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mean.</note>And that is mean, when a mans piſſing and his drinking is of like quantity. All this muſt be conſidered by due proportion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Contents.</note>The contents are all things in the water, that be of another matter and ſubſtance par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, then is the urine:<note place="margin">Sediment. Sublation. Cloud.</note> as the ſediment or ground, the ſublation or ſwim, and the cloud, To theſe are added other diſ-form contents, like hairs, like huskes, like bran,<note place="margin">Crown.</note> and ſuch other. And alſo the crown of the urine, with the bubles, and other things ſwimming on the top of it.</p>
               <p>For the better underſtanding of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, you muſt note that the whole urine from the top to the bottome, is divided com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly into three rooms or regions.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> rooms or Regions. Ground or Sediment.</note>The lowermoſt is the region of the ground or ſediment: ſo that the grounds or ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are the contents that occupie the lowermoſt region. Or yet more properly, the ſediment is called a certain ſubſtance of groſſer matter then is the urine, like to a quantity of very watery flegm, which ſleeteth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36549:22"/>
a little above the bottome of the urine: But if it be ſo light, that it ſwim in the middle region of the urine, then is it called the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limation or ſwim.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sublimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Swim.</note>And if it bee yet more lighter, ſo that it doth fleet in the higheſt part of the urine then it is called a cloud: whereby you may perceive that the ground,<note place="margin">Cloud.</note> the ſwim, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cloud are but one thing in ſubſtance, and differ onely by lightneſs and height, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his name according to the region that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> occupieth.<note place="margin">Another diviſion of the three Regions.</note> But yet again note, that ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one of the 3. regions, is farther devided int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other parts alſo; whereby you may know exactly, how far all contents differ from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> juſt room of their region; ſo that the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> urine muſt be divided into eleven juſt parts of which the nether region occupieth fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the fift is the void room between that an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the middle region, which containeth 3. more that is to ſay, the ſixt, ſeventh, and eigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And then the ninth is a void room between the middle region and the higheſt, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> higheſt region, containeth the other tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parts that remain, that is the tenth an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the eleventh, as this Figure ſheweth whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hereafter followeth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>urinal divided into sections for measuring urine</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bubbles.</note>Higheſt of all things in the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine are the bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther go about with the ring only, or elſe fleet in the middle of the urine onely, or elſe both. Yea ſometime they cover all the whole top of the urine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fattineſs.</note>Beſide theſe, there is oftentimes as it were flotes or fattineſs on the top, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time certain ſpots only, which are like to drops of oil. And theſe commonly are the whole contents. For as for gravell or ſtone, or any like thing is contained under the name of diſ-form contents.</p>
               <p>You ſhall alſo underſtand, that in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents muſt the ſubſtance, the quantity, and colour, bee obſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:36549:23"/>
                  <note place="margin">Subſtance.</note>The Subſtance is either equall or une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Equall.</note>Equal Subſtance is called, when the ground ſwim, or cloud, (for to them appertaineth this conſideration) is not tattered and diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but juſtly knit together.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Unequall.</note>Unequall is contrary, when it is thinner in one part then in another, or flittered out, and not joyntly and uniformly joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Quantitie.</note>The quantity muſt be conſidered in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to a mean, which if you know well, then may you ſoon judge that to bee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that is more then it: and that to be too little, that is leſſe then it: But this mean quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity muſt you learn of a perfect whole wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and beſt by the teaching of ſome good Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>Of colours I have ſpoken before ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for their varietie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> What a perfect <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine is, and alſo how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes all parts of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine may be altered in a healthful man.</head>
               <p>NOw that you know the difference o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch things that ought to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36549:23"/>
in urine, before you ſhal learn by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them, to judge of the perſon that made it, how he is diſpoſed in his body: you muſt firſt know how many waies the parts of the urine may bee changed in a healthfull man. For the better underſtanding of which thing, and of all that ſhall be ſaid hereafter, I will firſt define what a perfect whole urine is, which as it betokeneth no grief in it ſelf, ſo it is a true rule to examine all other urines by that, which are not whole, but declare in them ſome grief.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A perfect whole urine <hi>Galen c.</hi> 12. <hi>Criſib.</hi>
                  </note>A perfect whole urine is mean in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and in quantity, and in colour pale, or party ſaffron, with a white ground, duely knit and ſtable, without bubbles and other evill contents.</p>
               <p>So that this perfect whole urine declareth the difference of all other urines; For eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry urine the more it agreeth with this, the better it is: and the more it differeth from this, the worſe it is, as I ſhall anon particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly declare.</p>
               <p>And here you muſt mark, that this perfect whole urine is not only taken of a perfect whole man, but alſo of the luſtieſt time of mans age, that is at thirty yeers: or more largely, between twenty five and thirty five. For in every age doth the urine alter, as you ſhal hear by and by.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36549:24"/>
                  <head>The difference of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine by age in men.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Children.</note>THe Urine of children differeth but little in colour from pale, or light ſaffron and in ſubſtance it ſomewhat exceedeth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thickneſſe the ſubſtance of yong mens urine and hath much ground in it.<note place="margin">Galen <hi>2.</hi> preſag. Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> And the more they do grow in age, the higher waxeth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> colour,<note place="margin">Young men.</note> the ſubſtance the thinner, and the leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is the ground. And therefore when age i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moſt freſheſt,<note place="margin">Men.</note> the colour is pale (ſo that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> urine of flouriſhing youth or perfect man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hood, is pale or light ſaffron) and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> reſteth, and goeth no higher, and the groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of it is mean. But now after that time th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more age increaſeth and youth decayeth, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more the colour changeth from pale tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ard white,<note place="margin">Age.</note> and the ground waxeth leſſer an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> darker: ſo that the urine of old men is thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and white, with little ground, inclining un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to cruditie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine of Women by age.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Women.</note>THe Urine of women which are temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate in health and in their flouriſhin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> youth, doth decline ſomewhat from pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and light ſaffron toward white, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36549:24"/>
is in manner thin,<note place="margin">Young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> but it hath more ground then mens urine; now all they that be under this flouriſhing age, the younger they be, the whiter coloured is their urine, and the more ground it hath; and if they be elder, the more aged they are,<note place="margin">Aged wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> the whiter alſo is their urine, but the ground is everleſs and leſſe. And this you may ſee how both diverſity of age, and diverſitie alſo of kind or ſexe, cauſeth alteration in urine, without change of health; for you muſt underſtand all theſe ages with perfect health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The diverſity of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rines, according to the times of the yeer.</head>
                  <p>EVen as the diverſity of ages alters urine, ſo doth the times of the yeer. <note place="margin">Spring.</note>For the more that the ſpring time draws toward heat the more the urine gathereth high colour, departing from pale and flaxen, toward pale and light ſaffron: and the inequality of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance changeth into a due equality according to nature, and the ground doth waxe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and the quantity is more in reſpect to that is drunk: ſo that about the midſt of the ſpring they return to a mean.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Summer.</note>In the beginning of Summer, the colour appeareth pale and light ſaffron, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36549:25"/>
mean, the ground white, duly kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and ſtable, but yet thinner then a mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ground. And the more that the Summ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> proceedeth and draweth to the higheſt, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> leſſer is the quantity of urine, in compariſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the drink and the ground, changeth fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his naturall whiteneſs to a paliſh colour an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is much leſſer and thinner. And this thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe glyſtereth withall, and inclineth to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward golden and ſaffron colour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Harveſt.</note>When Harveſt commeth, then the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours do return to a mean again: but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thinneſs and brightneſs remaineth ſtill; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ground alſo is ſtill obſcure and little, but y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is white, duely knit and ſtable. And a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Harveſt goeth forward, ſo the urine retu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth to a mean in all things.</p>
                  <p>In the middle of winter and thereabou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the urine keepeth due quantitie, but the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour inclineth toward white, and the groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is over great, but in all other points it mean.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Winter.</note>And as Winter goeth on, the ſubſtance urine appeareth divers, and the colour whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the quantity greater in reſpect to the drin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and the contents greater and unconcoct but toward the ſpring time they return to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards a mean as I have before ſaid.</p>
                  <p>Yet beſide theſe, alſo diverſity of coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tries
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36549:25"/>
cauſeth diverſity of urine,<note place="margin">Countries alter urine.</note> even by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ame reaſons as doth the times of the yeer. For countries that be temperate exactly, make urine like unto the ſpring time. And thoſe countries that be hot and dry make urine like unto ſummer. And contrariwiſe, cold and moiſt alter water, as doth winter. But countries that are drie and diſtempered between heat and cold, make urine like har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Meats drinks and medicines.</note>Alſo meats and drinks, and order of diet, cauſeth urine to alter, and medicines alſo, as not only experience reacheth, but alſo <hi>Hippocrates</hi> witneſſeth in the ſixt Book of his <hi>Epidemies,</hi> (or raining ſickneſſes) in the fift part and the fifteenth ſentence, as for example:<note place="margin">Meats of light con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> Thoſe meats that are light of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction and good in ſubſtance, cauſe good and temperate urine with pure contents: but contrary meats cauſe diſcoloured urine, and thin, with ſtrange contents.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Meats of hard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction.</note>Meats that will not concoct, make leſſer contents, and divers in ſubſtance. Evill meats cauſe greater contents, and in nothing duely formed. And as the quality of meats doth alter urine, ſo doth the quantity alſo. For if a man have eaten much, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted it, his urine ſhall be thin and white, and ſometime without ground. But if this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36549:26"/>
crudity (or rawneſs in ſtomack) contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> long, the urine will become divers in ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance,<note place="margin">Drinking of wine.</note> and in contents.</p>
                  <p>Alſo wine drunk abundantly cauſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teration in urine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Faſting long.</note>But now contrariwiſe, if a man doe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> long, his urine will appear fiery and ſaffr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> coloured, and thin with leſſer ground</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Suffering of famine.</note>But if a man ſuffer famine, and do n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nouriſh, his water ſhall be thin and whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with a certain gliſtering, and witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ground.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Labour.</note>Moreover, exerciſe and reſt changeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rine: for through exceſſive labour, the uri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> changeth from light ſaffron, and at leng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> becommeth ſaffron coloured, with lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ground, thin, and higher coloured then ſhould be. And ſome time there fleete on the top a certain faſtneſs, ſpecially aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> overmuch wearineſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Reſt.</note>But idleneſs and reſt doth contrariwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cauſe white urine, with greater and groſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ground.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Sleep. Watching.</note>Furthermore ſleep, and watching, if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> exceed meaſure, they alter urine; but the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is a difference between both ſleepe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> watching comming of ſickneſs, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> both when they be taken willingly in heal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> For if that ſickneſs cauſe overmuch ſlee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:36549:26"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen is the urine whitiſh, with ſubſtance ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her fully thick, or but partly thin, and the contents many and undigeſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Naturall ſleep.</note>But if that ſuch ſleep come naturally the urine is not ſo white, but rather flaxen, and the ſubſtance mean, with greater and well concoct contents.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Voluntary ſleep.</note>And likewiſe they that have watched purpoſedly, and not by reaſon of ſickneſs, their urine is but little changed.<note place="margin">Watch in ſickneſs.</note> But if they watch for any ſickly cauſe, their urine will change but little at the beginning: but with continuance the contents will be diſperſed, and at the laſt clean waſted, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the urine waxeth thinner and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by little and little, and the colour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth either to white and watery, or unto golden ſaffron, oylie, or black, according as the cauſe is that maketh it ſo to change.</p>
                  <p>Of alteration by complexion, I will write in the next Chapter.</p>
                  <p>Now have you heard as touching altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of urine in health, according to diverſity of ages, both in men and women, times of the yeer, countries, meats and drinks, labour, reſt, ſleep, and watch: ſo that you muſt have regard to theſe in all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both in health and in ſickneſſe. For if theſe be not diligently marked, they may
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36549:27"/>
cauſe great error, as you may well co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">What is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in urine</note>Firſt therefore, in every urine you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> conſider, whether it be a mans or a wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and what age he or ſhee is of, then w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> time of the yeer it is, and what count what meats and drinks the perſon uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and likewiſe of labour and reſt, ſleep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> watch: And then muſt you conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> every one of theſe doth alter urine: ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> if the altering of them from that health urine (whereof I ſpake in the beginning this Chapter) be but ſuch as one of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> foreſaid things would cauſe, then may it be judged to come of any diſeaſe, as for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample. High coloured water in ſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (ſo that it paſs not ſaffron colour) or w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> coloured water in winter, ſhould rather reckoned to come of the time of the y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> then of any ſickneſs: and likewiſe of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> things.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> What be the generall qualities that alte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the parts of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
               <p>BEfore I treat of the ſignification of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> parts of Urine, I think it good to inſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36549:27"/>
you of the generall qualities which cauſe all alterations in urine: whereby you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not only what every urine doth beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken (as I ſhall anon ſet forth) but alſo if you mark well this Chapter, you ſhall ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he cauſe why every urine doth ſo ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie.</p>
               <p>You ſhall underſtand therefore, that there be four chief and only qualities, whereof all things that are both in the Sea and Earth are made: as man and beaſt, fiſh and fowl, trees, herbs, ſtones, and mettals. Theſe four qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities are heat, cold, moiſtneſs and drineſs: and theſe four continuing duly tempered (as nature ordered them firſt in every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect body) be the cauſe of continuall health. But if they bee altered wrongly, then doe they cauſe diſeaſes diverſly, according to the diverſitie of the alterations: And as they doe cauſe diſeaſes, ſo they change the colour, ſubſtance, and other parts of the urine, whereby wee may conjecture the cauſe of the diſeaſe; and ſo conſequently the diſeaſe it ſelf, though ſometime it declareth the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe it ſelf, and not the cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Paſſive and active qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</note>But now to come to the matter meeteſt for this time, you ſhall mark that two of theſe four qualities are named Paſſive, and they cauſe but ſmall alteration in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36549:28"/>
The other two are called Active, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they cauſe great alteration.</p>
               <p>The Active qualities are heat and col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the Paſſive qualities are drineſs an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moiſtneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Moiſtneſs.</note>When Moiſtneſs therefore exceedeth a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lone, it dulleth the naturall colour of urin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thicketh and ingroſſeth the ſubſtance, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> increaſeth the quantitie. And as the ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part of it above waxeth rough and trouble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo the ground increaſeth and continue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> raw and unconcoct.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dryneſs.</note>But dryneſs doth diminiſh the quantit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of urine, and alſo the contents: It maket<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it thin in ſubſtance, cleer and bright, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cauſeth mean colour, and the ground appea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth groſſer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Heat.</note>Likewiſe heat, if it exceed meaſure bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> little, it maketh pale and light ſaffron co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour in the urine. But if heat exceed great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly it cauſeth golden and ſaffron colour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with mean ſubſtance, and a little brightneſs the ground is mean, in reſpect to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of urine, but it declineth from the du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whiteneſs toward ſaffron colour.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cold.</note>But cold on the other ſide maketh urin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> turn to white colour, and changeth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from a mean. And if the cold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, the urine will alter from mean ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36549:28"/>
and therefore conſequently will bee either thin or groſſe. If it be thin or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, the ground ſhall be either obſcure and little, or much, and that divers and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct.</p>
               <p>And this is the working of theſe four qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities when they exceed alone.</p>
               <p>But and if two of them exceed together, there may reſult of that ſort four other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemperances; as hot and dry, hot and moiſt, cold and dry, and cold and moiſt.<note place="margin">Compound diſtempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of qualities.</note> Now what alterations theſe and every one of them doth cauſe the urine, you may eaſily conjecture, if you keep in mind that which I ſaid of the four ſimple qualities, and ſo adde togethet the alterations.</p>
               <p>And this muſt you remember therewith, that where they both agree in any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they cauſe that alteration to bee the greater: and where they be contrary, they cauſe the alteration to be nearer to a mean: howbeit ſomewhat to help you, take this brief declaration.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man.</note>As a temperate man doth make that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect urine, written of before, (<hi>in Chap.</hi> 6.) ſo the urine of a ſanguine man (which is hot and moiſt) ſhall be yellow, or light ſaffron coloured, by the reaſon of the heat, and ſomewhat groſs, by reaſon of the moiſture.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36549:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:36549:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36549:30"/>
                  <note place="margin">A cholerick man.</note>In a cholerick man (being hot and dry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the urine ſhall be in colour as in a ſanguin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man, but in ſubſtance thin, by reaſon of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dryneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colike man.</note>The urine of a melancholy man (whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture is cold and dry) ſhall be white throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the cold, and cleer for the dryneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick man.</note>The flegmatick man (which is cold an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moiſt) maketh urine white through cold, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thick by the moiſture, for as heat and col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> altereth the colours, ſo dryneſs and moiſtur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> changeth the ſubſtance. Now if you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remembred all that I have written before then ſhall you be the meeter and better a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble a great deal to perceive the reaſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the tokens which vrine doth give. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall your knowledge be the more certai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if you know not only the thing, but alſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe of it. Now therefore will I wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the ſignification of the parts of urin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> particularly, that you may perceive th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt, and chief commoditie of urine which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worketh for mans health.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:36549:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The ſignifications of the parts of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine particularly.</head>
               <p>I Told you in the ſixt Chapter of this Book what urine was moſt perfect, ſound, and healthfull of all other. And I ſaid, that it was the rule and tryall to examine all other urines by, ſo that the neerer that any urine was to it, the better it was; and the further that it declineth from it, the worſe it is. This I ſaid, ſhould be as a generall rule, which thing to be true in healthful men, you may perceive by that I have written already. And that it is alſo true in ſick men. <hi>Hypocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> witneſſeth, ſaying, <hi>That <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine is beſt, whoſe ground is white, duly knit and ſtable, all the time that the ſickneſs prevaileth.</hi> But <hi>Galen</hi> to ſupply that that is underſtood in this ſaying, and ſo to make it perfect, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thereto, <hi>That it muſt be of colour par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie golden or pale, and of a mean ſubſtance between thick and thin.</hi> And alſo in theſe things is required ſtableneſs, to make it a perfect Urine; for that which is unſtable in any part, in that it is not perfect.</p>
               <p>Here were a place to ſpeake of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of this changeableneſs or unſtableneſs;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36549:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for there is one ſort called ordinary, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other called unordinarie, and of both theſe are there divers differences. But becauſe they depend of an exacter judgement the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unlearned men can well attain unto, I over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs them for this time, and will declare the other differences of urine, whereby it alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from this mean urine, in all parts parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Subſtance or urine.</note>And firſt I will begin with the ſubſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of urine, the which (as I ſaid before) is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> three kindes, thick, thin, and mean.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mean.</note>A mean urine is that, that is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle between extream thick, and extrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thin. And as it is mean between them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubſtance, ſo is it mean in ſignification, ſo it doth betoken (of it ſelf) only good tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perance and health. But the other two beto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken diſtemperance and default of concoct<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, and that diverſly, according to the diver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſity of the cauſes of them, as you ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſequently hear.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thin urine.</note>Firſt to ſpeak of thin urine, either it doth ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> continue thin, as it was firſt made, or elſe it doth ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly waxe thick and troubled. That that doth contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtill thin doth betoken lack of concoction, and ſo do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the other alſo; but yet this that continueth thin be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keneth more lack of conoction, for it betokene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that nature hath not yet begun to concoct. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therefore is that water, a ſign of extream crud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or rawneſs in nature. But that that waxeth thick,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36549:31"/>
it beginneth to cool, though it betoken lack of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, yet doth it declare that nature hath begun to concoct alreadie, notwithſtanding it is an evill urine, for it ſignifieth that nature hath need not only of great ſtrength to perform that concoction which ſhe hath begun; but alſo that there is required long time to the performance of the ſame. For the which cauſe, <hi>Galen</hi> calleth this, <hi>Of all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rines the worſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have you heard touching crudity and concoction, what thin urine doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, ſo that all thin urine betokeneth crudity. And beſide that doth further betoken (as witneſſeth <hi>Hypocrates) gatherings or apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumations in the nether parts of the bodie,</hi> namely, <hi>if it continue ſo very long, and the patient eſcape death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thin and white.</note>Furthermore, if ſuch thin urine have with it a light whiteneſs, it is a very evill ſign. For if it be in a burning ague, it is a token of frenſines. But if the patient be franſick alreadie, and the urine doth ſo continue, it doth moſt commonly betoken death. And if he eſcape death (the which is ſeldome ſeen) then ſhall he be long ſick, and eſcape hardly.</p>
               <p>Thin urine alſo betokeneth divers other things: as the ſtopping of the reins, and of the water veins. And likewiſe, if a man have had much bleeding, or laxe, or piſſing, his urine will be white and thin, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt without ground: Like manner in old
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36549:32"/>
age, and long weakneſs of ſickneſs. Alſo in young children if it continue long, it is a deadly ſign.</p>
               <p>Yet thin urine doth ſometime betoken the end of ſickneſs and recovery of health: as in Agues (namely quotidians) if at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of them and ſo after, the urine did appear thick and troubled, and eſpecially if the colour amend therewith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thin and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>axen.</note>And if it be thin in ſubſtance, and of flaxen colour, then is it better then thin and white: for becauſe the colour is better though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſubſtance bee all one; ſo that though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it betoken ſome weakneſs and lack of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, yet not ſo much as doth the other, for the colour is meanly concoct: that is to ſay, naturall heat is meanly increaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thin and golden.</note>But if it be thin and golden, it is ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more better then thin and flaxen: for the colour is more exact and this betokeneth concoction half compleat, for that which it lacketh in ſubſtance, it hath in colour.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thin and ſaffron.</note>After this is there thin and ſaffron colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which betokeneth firſt lack of concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and beſide that default of nouriſhment as in a young man that faſteth long: And ſometime it betokeneth that exceſs of her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the inner parts of the body, doth cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cholerick humours to abound, as in the feve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:36549:32"/>
tertian. Beſide all this, it betokeneth thought, carefulneſs, and watching, and alſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much labour, and taking of heat in the Sun.</p>
               <p>And thus have you heard the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thin urine, both alone, and alſo with ſuch colours as it can be coupled.</p>
               <p>Now ſhall you hear what thick urine doth betoken, both alone, and alſo with ſuch divers colours, as it may be coupled.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick.</note>Thick urine (which is, ſo I mean, when it is firſt made) either it doth continue ſtill thick, or elſe it doth ſettle, and waxe clear. If it continue ſtill thick, it betokeneth that that diſturbance which was in the bloud, that is to ſay, the rage of ſickneſſe doth ſtill continue ſtrongly: and that naturall ſtrength is but weak. This urine is not ſo good as that which doth ſettle and waxe cleer. For that doth betoken that the diſeaſe ſhal ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be overcome: howbeit there remaineth yet ſomewhat of that diſtemperate trouble in the blood: yet nature hath the over-hand and expelleth the matter of the grief, and therefore is ſuch a urine called good, but yet it betokeneth ſome lack of concoction, though not ſo much as that which continueth troubled and thick ſtill.</p>
               <p>Alſo thick urine (if it be exceeding thick) doth betoken death, as <hi>Hypocrates</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36549:33"/>
And the urine that is thick and troubled, lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beaſts urine, doth betoken head ach, eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preſent already, or ſhortly after to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> If thick urine appeare in an ague, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thin urine went before, it betokeneth tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſickneſs will abate ſtraightwaies, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> declareth that nature hath overcome the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of the ſickneſs: but if it appear thick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the beginning of the ague, and do not wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thin in proceſs of time, it betokeneth plent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of matter, and weakneſs of nature; ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is fear leſt nature ſhould be overcom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> except the colour do amend.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick and white.</note>Thick urine alſo betokeneth openne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the water pipes and reins. And if it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thick and white, it betokeneth great plen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of raw humours, and ſundry kinds of fleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be gathered in the bodie: and betokene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo (namely if it be much) that thoſe gath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rings, which might be looked for in ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> agues ſhall not enſue, for the matter whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould cauſe them departeth out by urine but the whiteneſs of this urine is bright ſnow. For if it be ſomewhat darker li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the whiteneſs of milk, it is a token of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtone, either in the bladder or reins, namely if ſuch urine chance in the end and amendin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſickneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Grey.</note>But if the colour of it be grey, it betokene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:36549:33"/>
not only plenty of matter in the body, but alſo that the whole body is poſſeſſed with a dangerous ſickneſs, whereof oftentimes it chanceth the patient to break out with bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and heat in his skin.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick and claret.</note>Next after this followeth thick claret co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour (for flaxen, yellow, nor ſaffron colour doth not agree with thick urine) and it doth ſignifie that the diſeaſe ſhall continue long, ſpecially if the ground of it be alſo of claret colour. But yet this diſeaſe without perill of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick and red.</note>Thick urine, if it be red coloured, doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token abundance of blood, as is ſeen in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall Agues, and in all perillous Agues, as witneſſeth <hi>Theophylus.</hi> If this water come by little and little, it is an evill token, for it doth alwaies declare danger.</p>
               <p>And if that ſort of urine (in ſuch Agues) do waxe troubled, ſo that there come with it deafneſs of hearing, and ach of the head, with pain in the neck and in the ſides of the belly, it betokeneth that the Patient ſhall have the falling evill within a ſeven night.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick and crimſon.</note>And if a thick urine have a crimſon colour, If it bee burning Agues, and the Patient then have the headach, it betokeneth that a chief criticall ſign either is then preſent, or elſe nigh at hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:36549:34"/>
                  <note place="margin">Thick and blew.</note>But if the urine be thick and blew colo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, it ſignifieth diverſly, as the perſons a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that made it. For in them that are in wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of recovery, it betokeneth that they ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſcape their grief. It ſignifieth alſo pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the water-pipes, or elſe that the par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath runn much.</p>
               <p>And if it appear ſuch in old men, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> continue long, it declareth not only that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bladder is infected with evill humours, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commonly alſo that he ſhall be rid of them But if it come after the grief of the ſtone, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> declareth that the grief ſhall be turned int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſtrangurie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick and green.</note>Thick urine and green, namely in Ague<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a token of the yellow Jawnders, eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preſent, or ready to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick and aſh colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>Thick urine and aſh coloured, if it appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Agues and do not ſettle, it is a ſign of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, But in the burning Ague, it betoken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the ſtrangurie will come ſhortly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thick and black.</note>But if a black colour appear in thick urine it betokeneth ſometime well, as in the end of the Fever Quarten, and of melancholike madneſs, for it betokeneth that the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholike matter, which cauſed the diſeaſes, doth avoid out.</p>
               <p>But ſometimes it is an evill token, for it ſignifieth that either the blood is burned
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36549:34"/>
through exceeding heat, or elſe that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll heat is clean quenched through deadly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld, and therefore is commonly called a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adly ſign, namely in ſharp Agues, if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve an evill ſavour. And ſo meaneth <hi>Galen,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen he ſaith, that he marked, <hi>The thicker <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at a black water is, the worſe it is,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oreover, <hi>That he never ſaw any eſcape, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich made ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus have you heard of the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons of thin and thick urine, with ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ours as may be coupled therewith.</p>
               <p>Now will I write a little of the colours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one, and of ſuch tokens as come chiefly of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, rather then of the ſubſtance or any other part of the urine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Colours of urine.</note>The colours of urine declare commonly, how heat and cold do reign in the body, ſo that the whiter the urine is, the greater is the cold, and natural heat leſſe; and the higher coloured that the urine is, the greater is the heat.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">White.</note>But to ſpeak particularly, that you may perceive it the better. If the urine be white, it is a ſign that concoction faileth quite, and the lighter coloured, the worſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pale.</note>Pale colour is better ſomewhat, though it alſo declare lack of naturall heat and ſtrength.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Flaxen.</note>And flaxen colour, though it betokeneth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36549:35"/>
beginning of concoction, yet it is not pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect: howbeit it may be well taken, if all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſigns be good.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pale, light ſaffron.</note>Pale and light ſaffron (as you have hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before) are the beſt colours and moſt temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate, which betoken exact concoction.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Golden ſaffron.</note>But golden and ſaffron colour declare e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſs of heat.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Claret red. Crimſon Purple. Green oily.</note>Claret is next, and then red, after it crim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, and then purple, then green, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of them is oily urine, which as they goe in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, ſo they declare greater and greater he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with increaſe, not only of the qualitie, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo of the matter containing the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Blew aſh-colour.</note>But now of the other ſide, blew urine, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aſh colour, are tokens of exceſſive cold ſometime with matter, and ſometime with out; and ſo likewiſe of black urine, howbe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>it it cometh ſometime of exceſs of heat.</p>
               <p>But how you may know the difference both of it and all the other, now will I ſhew in order, with the reſt of their ſignifications</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">White.</note>White urine, if it come in great quantity in a whole man, it betokeneth much drink<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of thin wine.</p>
               <p>But if it be mean in quantity, with a due ground, it declareth cold diſtemperance of the liver. The urine doth appear white, with a diſ-form and unconcocted ground, in them
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36549:35"/>
that have the dropſie. But in old men, white <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rine is no great evill ſign, as you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eive by that I ſaid before of Ages, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey alter urine. But in yong men, and ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s are of freſheſt age, it is a worſe ſign, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pecially if it have either no contents, or elſe evill contents. And if urine continue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong time white without changing, it beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth painfull beating of the head, daſelling of the eies, and giddineſs, and alſo the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing evill, lothſomneſs of good meats, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſting ſometime after evill meats, greedie hunger, pain in limbs, and painfull moving of the ſinewes, and divers griefes of the head and reines, and alſo pain in the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament, and great weakneſs by ſickneſs, for all theſe doe follow continually lack of concoction, either cold, or ſtopping of the urines and conduct, or tranſpoſing of the humours.</p>
               <p>But the differences of theſe cannot eaſily bee known of every man, yet ſuch as are learned may gather certain diſtinctions of them by the accidents which follow diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Milk white, hornwhite, gray.</note>Dark white colours, as milk white, white, white like horn, and grey, If they appear in the beginning of Agues, and in the increaſe of them, they doe betoken much pain. But
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36549:36"/>
in the decreaſe of Agues, they declare he eſpecially if it come plentifully.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pale, flaxen</note>Pale urine and flaxen, do not lightly pear in Agues, except they be eaſie Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſhort, as thoſe which continue but day, but if that it do follow after bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Agues, it declareth that they be fully d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pale, ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron.</note>As for pale and light ſaffron, they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I ſaid before) the beſt and moſt perfect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lours, namely, in young men and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> youth. But in old men, women and child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (whoſe urine, as I have ſaid, declineth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward white and pale) it doth betoken t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their bodie is too hot, either by reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their diet, or elſe of their exerciſe. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as much as it is but mean exceſſe, it declare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but ſmall grief.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Golden ſaffron co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</note>Golden and ſaffron coloured urine, if be either ſomewhat thin, or very thick, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it hath no ground, or elſe very few, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dark contents. But in this they differ, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> golden urine declareth exceſs of heat, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> matter alſo, by reaſon of meats, ſharp med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cines, chafing of the bloud through ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heat of the bowels, or elſe heat of the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the yeer.</p>
               <p>But ſaffron colour appeareth rather wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> default of matter, through ſome affection o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:36549:36"/>
the mind, watching, heat of the ſun, labour, and ſuch like things, which increaſe thin and yellow choller, and diminiſh naturall heat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o that the cauſe of this colour is choler it ſelf, increaſed either in quantity, or elſe in qualitie. But in old men and women, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch other, there is ſome greater cauſe that occaſioneth it, for it ſignifieth an Ague com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth of ſaffronly choler diſperſed through the whole body; after which there followeth commonly giddineſs, headach, bitterneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he mouth, lothſomeneſs of meat, thirſtineſs, Alſo in yong men, ſuch urine is cauſed through much exerciſe, and uſe of hot meats.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Claret and red <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Claret urine.</note>CLaret and red urine is coloured either of the mixture of red choler, or elſe of the corruption of bloud; ſuch urine oftentimes goeth before Agues. For when the blood doth ſo abound, that it cannot be duly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured, nor can take no ayre, there is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred a certain corruption, which as it is red of colour it ſelf, ſo it cauſeth the urine to be red in colour if it be much, elſe it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth only claret colour. But if it be exact red lik grain, it betokeneth that bloud iſſueth into it, out of ſome veins nigh to the reins,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36549:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:36549:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:36549:38"/>
which either are broken, or other waies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened. But how it may be known fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whence it commeth, and how, there are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny means to ſearch, but becauſe they are<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> light to perceive, I will reſerve them for P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſicians that are learned. This colour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſelf is no great evill ſign, namely in yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> men, for it betokeneth exceſs of bloud, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may well bee born of them. But in old m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is a very evill ſign, for it betokeneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther long ſickneſs, or elſe death, ſith na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is ſo weak that it cannot keep in her natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> humour. And if that red colour, come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> red choler, as it doth in young men, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> moſt part and not of blood (which thing learned Phyſician may conjecture partly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the former diet, and other ſigns more) t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> accidents ſhal be the more troublous; ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit yet not ſo evill, as when it commeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſaffron or golden choler, for this cauſe greater thirſt, and more troublous ſleep th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Crimſon colour.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Crimſon colour.</note>CRimſon colour is a token that the goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> humours of the bodie are burned, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> turned into red or black choler, which cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worſe griefs then the other; howbeit if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:36549:38"/>
have a good ground, the grief is the more moderate: But if it have either no contents for a ſpace, or elſe evill contents, and the urine appear like a thick myſte, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what gliſtering light, it is a ſign that nature needeth ſuch ſtrength to recover her ſelfe to her own ſtate. Notwithſtanding ſuch u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine is cauſed ſometime in whole folk, by reaſon of much labour, and long journying, and then it hath ſome good ſigns therewith. But in them that have a ſharp Ague, ſuch crimſon colour of urine doth betoken that corrupt blood doth abound, and that it doth putrifie, and turn into choler. And commonly they that make ſuch urine, doe thirſt much, and are dry in their mouth, and are troubled in their ſleep, and feel ſharp Agues, and are half diſtract, and feel pain of the liver with coughing.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit, yet theſe ſigns may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as well good as bad, according as the colours do change to better or worſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Purple Colour.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Purple co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</note>PUrple colour declareth need of much ſtrength before it can be altered to a good urine.</p>
                  <p>This urine is a ſign of burning choler. And if it do continue very long, it is a token
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36549:39"/>
of the yellow Jaunders, with abundance groſs and corrupt choller, gathered in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver. And at the beginning there goeth w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it ſome ſpices and grudgings of the Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with a little thirſtineſs; but unleſs there b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſcretion uſed in the diet of ſuch a Patie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it may turn to a much worſe diſeaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Green <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rines.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Green co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</note>GReen colour is an evill and a dangero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> token, for it needeth not only long tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but alſo cotinual ſtrength to bring it ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to a good trade. The higher that this cold is, the more it declareth that choller exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth the other humours: which if it be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more burned, will cauſe black urine, which I will anon ſpeak. But if green o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour come of waſting of the fat, then is ſomewhat like to oylie colour, or popin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> green: but if it come of abundance of purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh colour, and through increaſe of his qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie, then doth the colour incline more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward black, and gliſtereth with ſhadow green, drawing very nigh unto black. Af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> green choler followeth madneſs, parbrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, and avoiding of choler, ſometimes wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> matter, or elſe burned: and alſo continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thirſtineſs, and burning heat of the tongue
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36549:39"/>
ſtraightneſs about the ſtomack. And like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things. But if the patient continue ſtrong, and the colour of the urine do waxe lighter, there is good hope, elſe there is great fear, leaſt of the dryneſs and burning, there do follow contraction of the ſinews, which will kill the patient.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Oilie <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, or Popinjay Green.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Oilie urine, or popinjay green.</note>OYlie Urine is of three ſorts, as I ſaid in the fift Chapter, that is, light oylie, ſtark oylie, and dark oylie.</p>
                  <p>Oylie urines are a token of unnatural heat, and the higher that the colour is, the greater is the heat. And alſo they betoken melting of the fat within a man, for of it are they ſo coloured. But at the beginning, when there is a little fat melted, the urine is light oylie. For if it look ſtark oylie, then it ſignifieth that the diſeaſe increaſeth. But if it come once to dark oylie, then is the diſeaſe ſore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in the ſeventh Book of his <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> ſpeaking of fatneſs in urine, ſaith thus: <hi>Who ſo maketh urine with fatty flotes comming much and faſt, they have ſharp pains in the reins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which ſentence though it ſeem more to appertain to the contents then to the colour,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36549:40"/>
yet doth not onely <hi>Galen,</hi> but alſo <hi>Aetin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Actuarius,</hi> and alſo another <hi>Grecian,</hi> (who name I know not) expound it amongſt co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lours: and by it declare the difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> know whether that waſt or melting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fat be in the reins it ſelf, or in other parts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the body. For if it come faſt together, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith) then commeth it from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reins it ſelf, and betokneth the waſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be in them. But if it come ſoftly and increa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by little and little, then doth it declare th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the whole body is overcome with unna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turall heat, and that the fat of it doth waſt it doth betoken (as <hi>Act.</hi> witneſſeth) a waſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Ague; conſuming the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of blew <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, Aſh-colour, and Black.</head>
                  <p>BLew colour, Aſh-colour, and Black do differ only in lightneſs and darkneſs For aſh-colour is darker then blew: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> black is darker then any of them both.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Blew co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</note>Blew colour ſometime cometh of mode<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate melancholy, and then is the urine ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>what thin in ſubſtance. And ſometime i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> commeth of great cold, and then it is thick in ſubſtance. And ſometime it is a token o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mortifying of ſome part. Yea, and ſometime even of whole nature: namely, if the colour change to worſe and worſe, and there went
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36549:40"/>
before no token of concoction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Aſh-colour.</note>Aſh coloured urine commeth of like cauſes, and betokeneth like things. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it is ſo coloured many times, when the party that made it, hath been ſore beaten and bruiſed. But in this you need not the help of urine, for you may ſee the walts and tokens of the ſtripes in his body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Black urine.</note>Urine which is extream black, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time betokeneth extream heat, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time extream cold, the which both you may diſtinctly diſcerne, if you doe obſerve or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of alteration in the colours of the urine that the patient made laſt before. For if his urine before were green, or like thereto, then doth the black urine which follows it, betoken extream heat. But if it were laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore blew or aſh-coloured, then doth it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie extream cold. This black colour though it be commonly an evill and deadly ſign, as I ſaid before, (ſpeaking of thick urine and black) yet ſometime it is a good token.</p>
                  <p>For in all diſeaſes lightly that come of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy matter, it betokeneth that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth avoid, and ſo the ſicknes to end. And ſuch urine doth appear many times after pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations or other meats and drinks which purge the ſplene; namely, if a man do labour upon them, that was before diſeaſed of the ſpleen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:36549:41"/>Howbeit, ſometime meats and drinks of li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> colour cauſe black urine, as <hi>Galen</hi> witneſſeth namely, <hi>after dark red wine, and Allegant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But in moderate Agues, if ſuch black <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rine doe appear, it is a token of death, excep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it be on ſome Criticall dayes. And likewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in ſharp agues, eſpecially if the ſavour b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtrong and ſtinking: unleſs it come of ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> grief of the bladder</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Quantitie of urine.</note>Let this ſuffice for this time, as touchin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> colours. Now for the quantitie of urine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> when it is mean, it is a good token: ſo whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is either too much, or too little, it is an e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vill ſign, except it come of ſuch cauſe, (as ſhewed before) that altereth urine in healthfull man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Much in a whole body.</note>As firſt exceſſive quantitie of urine, com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth of much drinking of thin wine, as Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſh wine, and ſuch like. But that ſhall yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thus know: for the colour will be white<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and the ſubſtance thinner then a mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the contents alſo will be divers, and not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly knit. Likewiſe if there be aboundanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of raw humours in a man unconcocted, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yet nature perſevering ſtrong, then is ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> great quantity of urine, and ſomewhat thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of ſubſtance, but not ſo white as the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and the contents of this are better. Alſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith) <hi>much <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine made i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:36549:41"/>
the night,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4. Aph. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>is a token of ſmall ſege;</hi> ſo that if any impediment let naturall ſege, then will the quantity of urine be the greater. But in this as the colour is mean, ſo is the ground both greater and groſſer, yet in healthfull folk may the urine, by another means alſo be greater then a mean, and that may be by medicines which provoke urine, but then is the colour more naturall then the laſt that I ſpake of, and the ground is thinner of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo that it is dark and ſcarcely ſeene, and then is there a certain gliſtering in the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Little urine in a whole body.</note>Now contrarie waies, and of contrary cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes cometh ſmall quantitie of urine. For it cometh ſometime of lack of drinke, or dry meats, and then is the colour light ſaffron, with a ſmal ground, but yet ſomewhat groſs. Alſo both meats and medicines that are clammie, and apt to ſtop the water-pipes, do cauſe little urine, but then is the ground alſo little and thin.</p>
                  <p>Beſides theſe, much ſege cauſeth urine to be leſſer, for if the one excrement be greater then nature would, the other muſt needs be leſſe, if the body be healthful. In this urine, as you may partly know the cauſe of it by the knowledge of the exceſſive ſege, ſo will the urine it ſelf be thinner, and the ground very
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36549:42"/>
dark, thin, and not duely knit. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> many waies may this alteration appear in healthfull body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Much urine in a ſick bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note>Now in a ſick perſon, much urine eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> betokeneth the dropſie, and then is it lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> water, with a raw and diverſe ground or elſe if it be white, thin, and witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ground, then doth it betoken the piſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vill. And this urine (as witneſſeth <hi>Galen</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in his firſt Book of Judicials) <hi>is the worſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> any other of like ſort,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Diabete.</note> I mean which decla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lack of concoction, for it declareth the decay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yea I may ſay, the utter extinction of tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> naturall powers, that is, the retentive power and the alterative power alſo.</p>
                  <p>Much urine, in colour fierie, and light ſaf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fron, or of any like colour, is to be feared namely, if it be coupled with evill contents But if it be of crimſon or purple colour and ſo proceed, eſpecially if no concoctio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> went before it, then doth it encline to evill and betokeneth a certain mortifying and wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſting of the whole compoſition of the body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if much urine come in an Ague, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly toward the end, and that there went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it little urine, thick and ruddie, then is that a good token,<note place="margin">4. Aph 69.</note> as witneſſeth <hi>Hypocrates</hi> for it betokeneth the Ague to be at an end. And this Urine will bee white and thin
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36549:42"/>
moderately, and will have a mean ground.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Little urine in a ſick bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note>Now little quantity of urine, with a groſſe ground, unduly knit and unconcoct, is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill token; for it betokeneth the weakneſs of the alterative power, which is not able to extenuate, concoct, neither alter the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and therefore doth it with much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty paſs forth in ſuch groſsnes. Howbeit, if there follow after it a more thinner urine, with the ground well and duly knit, and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then is it without fear. For this latter u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine (as you heard before) is a token that the cauſe of the other is overcome and vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
                  <p>This little quantitie of urine cometh ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in vehement Agues, and then is the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent heat, cauſe thereof. Sometime alſo it cometh of the ſtopping of the water-pipes, not only through clammy meats and drinks, but alſo of ſome diſeaſe or grief in them.</p>
                  <p>And this now ſhall ſuffice for an Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, as touching the ſubſtance, colours, and quantitie of urine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Contents.</note>It followeth next, to ſpeak of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents which ſo greatly help to the right judgement of urine, that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> (in his ſecond book of Prognoſtications) doth by them only; yea, and that by one of them (I mean the ground (pronounce the judgement
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:36549:43"/>
of a perfect urine; ſaying, <hi>That that is the beſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sediment.</note> 
                     <hi>which hath his ſediment or ground, white, duly knit and ſtable, and that continually all the time of the ſickneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now ſeeing this great Clerk and Father of Phyſick, doth thus eſteem the ground, it ſhall not ſeem unmeet, that I orderly doe write briefly of thoſe principall things that are to be conſidered, as touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents; and firſt of all of the ground, which hath alteration (as you have heard) both in ſubſtance, colour, and quantitie.</p>
                  <p>But now as touching the ſubſtance? then is it only mean, when the third concoction in the veins is perfect. For the ground is the excrement (as you might ſay) of that third concoction, and is like in forme to matter, ſave that it is more duly knit together then is matter, and doth not ſmell ſo evill as it; or elſe you may liken it to thin ſteam.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Groſſe ground.</note>This Ground is then groſs, when the veins are repleniſhed with raw humors. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit this groſſeneſs or thickneſs is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes an evill token; for ſometime it is a ſign that nature hath prevailed againſt the crude humours which cauſed diſeaſes, and doth expell ſuch ſuperfluous excrements. And that ſhall you diſcerne by the goodneſs, of the colour, and alſo if it come in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36549:43"/>
of the ſickneſs: for if it come at the beginning, either in the increaſe of the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, then are they to be ſuſpected as evill; eſpecially if they bring with them evill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Thin ground.</note>A thin ground, being alſo pure, and ſo cleaving to the bottom of the Urinal, that it will not lightly riſe, though the urinall be ſhaked, it is a token of great weakneſs of nature in the third concoction, and ſuch a ground appeareth moſt in white and watrie urine. Howbeit ſometime a thin ground cometh by the reaſon that the raw humors are extenuate through naturall heat, which getting new ſtrength, doth extenuate and diſperſe all groſsneſs of raw humors within the veins. For the propertie of heat, is to knit and bind together thin things, and to extenuate and diſperſe groſſe and raw things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Colour of the groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>Now as touching the colours of the ground, the perfect ground is neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding white, neither yet pale, but mean between both, for if there appear any ſuch exceſſive white, then is it ſome rag of phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick matter, or elſe matter extreamly concocted, which commeth from ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward member being ſore; and that you may diſcern (as I ſaid before) by the toughnes, and by the ſavour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:36549:44"/>And if any man be deſirous to know the cauſe why the ground is white of colour, let him remember, that the ground is the ſuperfluous excrement of the bloud being perfectly concocted in the veins. Now that the bloud it ſelf, when it is exactly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, is turned into a white, or at leaſt, a party white colour, you may conjecture by the generation of milke, and alſo the ſeed of man, yea, and of matter, which all three are nothing elſe but bloud, exactly concocted, ſave that matter cometh of evill bloud.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pale. Flaxen.</note>And therefore whenſoever the ground hath in it any other colour then white, it is no good token: As firſt, if it be pale and flaxen coloured, then it is ſwarved from his right and commendable colour. Howbeit, yet it may be born as but meanly evill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that that colour commeth of ſmall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of choler.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Saffron. <hi>Actuarius.</hi>
                     </note>But if it be more higher coloured by cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, ſo that it be ſaffron coloured, then is it an evill token (as <hi>Actuarius</hi> ſaith) for it declareth that choler is exceſſively increaſed, either by the order of diet, or elſe by the corruption of bloud, or ſome other wayes.<note place="margin">7. Aph. 32.</note> Howbeit <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſms,</hi> ſeemeth to ſay the contrary, for he ſaith, <hi>That when the ground is ſo colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36549:44"/>
of choler, eſpecially if at the beginning of the ſickneſſe it were waterie to ſight, then doth it betoken a quicke ſickneſs;</hi> that is to ſay, as <hi>Philotheus</hi> expoundeth it,<note place="margin">Philotheus.</note> a ſickneſſe, that will ſhortly be ended, and ſo it may juſtly be called a good ſign. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding as in this point it is a good token, in that it ſignifieth that the diſeaſe is nigh the end, ſo it may be called (as <hi>Actua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> calleth it) an evill ſign, becauſe it doth betoken a cholerick ſickneſs, and that cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler doth unnaturally abound.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Antonius Muſa.</note>And if this anſwer do not content you, (though it content <hi>Antonius Muſa</hi>) then may you ſay more better (as I thinke) thus: That if the ground be at the beginning of the ſickneſs coloured with choller, and ſo increaſe (as <hi>Actuarius</hi> ſeemeth to mean) then is it an evil token indeed, for it declareth both the abundance, and alſo the encreaſe of choler. But if the ground, at the beginning of a cholerick diſeaſe were warry, that is, white and thin, and afterward turn to ſaffron co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, which is the exact colour of choler: or elſe to a yellow colour (which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſſe cholerick) then is it a token that the cholerick matter, which before lay lurking in the body, doth now begin to avoid; and ſo the cauſe of ſickneſſe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36549:45"/>
thus by nature expelled, health muſt nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> follow.</p>
                  <p>As contrariwiſe, if after yellow or ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fron colour it change unto whiter, and the be no certain token of concoction, then it an evill ſign, and a token of phrenſie. How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit, if there be any token of certain con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coction, then is the ſame a good ſign, that if you take heed, you may perceiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> here what a neceſſary thing it is to obſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> order in the alteration of urine, of whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I have partly ſpoken before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Claret co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. Red. Bloudie.</note>Now therefore to goe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ground bee of claret colour, either red o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> blew, the token is not good. For theſe bloo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy colours come either of too much abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dance of bloud, or elſe by reaſon that the retentive power is ſo feeble, that it canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> keep in the good humors, but ſuffreth them to run out.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Claret red.</note>Claret colour and red, doe betoken a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain default of concoction in the veins, and that through the exceſs of red choler. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yet this default is but mean and without danger, ſeeing that the hurt is only by quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, whereas ſome other do hurt both by quantitie and qualitie alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Bloudie.</note>Bloodie grounds are altogether worſe then red (though they be better then aſh-coloured,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36549:45"/>
and black) for they betoken that the bloud is nothing duely wrought, eſpecially if their quantitie be much, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, for then the quantity of matter doth let the powers to work, which thing yet as it may be born, ſo it declareth need of long time to recover health.</p>
                  <p>But if this doe come through weakneſs of the powers in themſelves, then is it an extream evill ſign: for it betokeneth that the powers are overcome with wearineſs in working, and be not able to keep in the good and profitable humors. Which thing to diſcern more exactly, you ſhall take arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall conjectures by other circumſtances, which give alſo tokens of judgement; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as by the age of the perſon, by his order of dyet, and ſuch like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Blew. Aſh-colour Black.</note>Now to make an end with the other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours which are of a dark hew, as blew-aſh-colour and black: Theſe of all other are the worſt, and moſt envious to nature, and the nearer they cleave to the bottome of the urinall, the worſe they are.</p>
                  <p>Theſe colours come of a black melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humour, being ingendred within the veins, or elſe coming from ſome other part into them: or elſe it betokeneth deadly mortifying. But ſometimes it cometh of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36549:46"/>
ſore bruiſing and ſtripes, and generally cometh (namely the black) either of exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſive cold or exceſſive heat.</p>
                  <p>And now for a concluſion, whatſoever have ſaid of the ground, you ſhall unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand the ſame to bee ſpoken of the ſwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and the cloud; for they are in kinde but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thing, ſave that they differ in lightneſs an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heft, and therefore alſo in places: But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> judgement of their ſubſtance and colour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> much after one rate, though ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence there be, as you ſhall hear hereafter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Quantitie</note>And likewiſe of their quantity, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as it is then only commendable when it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mean, ſo if it be greater then a mean, it dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> declare ſome alteration in man, though no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alwayes extreamly evill, for ſometime it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a token of fatting, or growing to a corpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rateneſs,<note place="margin">Great.</note> and that it doth ſignifie, if non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> other evill ſign be coupled with it. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> though the perſon feed much on nouriſhing meats, and that with reſt and an idle life, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> naturall heat appeareth ſo ſtrong, that ſhe can eaſily concoct ſuch meats. According to this ſaith <hi>Galen</hi> in his Judicials, that the plenty of the ground in urine betokeneth certain and exact with concoction: And that as the body is repleat with crude humours, ſo it declareth that thoſe ſame be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36549:46"/>
in expelling out at that preſent time. And for this cauſe (ſaith he) in all children com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, and in men alſo which feed much, or bee of ſome other cauſe replete with humors, their urine hath a great ground.</p>
                  <p>Alſo oftentimes it chanceth the pores of the skin to be ſtopped, ſo that ſuch excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as were wont to paſs out by them, are inforced to ſeek a new paſſage, which they find moſt readieſt by the urine, and thereof are the contents, and namely the ground, oftentimes encreaſed. And all theſe waies chance in health. But in ſickneſs, it chanceth many and groſſe ſuperfluities do appear in the urine, as often as the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall powers, namely, the alterative or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctive power being weakned, ſuch crude humours paſs out undefied.</p>
                  <p>So doth it chance (as witneſſeth <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Trallianus) That the urine of them which have the Collick,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tral. 2. cap. 33.</note> 
                     <hi>is flegmatick and hath a great ground.</hi> But if the contents be either great, or groſs in the beginning, or in the augmenting of ſickneſs, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if the Patient have any notable Ague) it argueth abundance of humours, to the concoction of the which there needeth both ſtrength of naturall powers, with time and good ſpeed.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:36549:47"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:36549:47"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:36549:48"/>
                     <note place="margin">Little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.</note>And now contrary wayes muſt you judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the ſmalneſs of the contents, for they be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſed either of great labour, long faſting ſtopping, or obſtruction of the veins, and ſuch like parts, or elſe of ſlackneſſe of concoction.<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>2.</hi> preſ. Hip. <hi>26.</hi>
                     </note> And (as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith) when the body is replete with crude and raw hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, then is the ground great, but if the body be repleniſhed with cholerick humors, then is there in the urine either little ground or none at all; but in ſuch caſe it is well, if there be any ſublimation or ſwim.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Urine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ground.</note>Now ſeemeth the place moſt meet to ſpeak of ſuch urines as have no ground at all, nor other orderly content, and that will I doe by the order of the colours of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, according as <hi>Actuarius</hi> proceedeth.</p>
                  <p>The urine that is very white, and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thin, and ſo lacketh the ground, doth betoken either ſome notable obſtruction, either immoderate cold, or elſe cruditie and lack of concoction. And as theſe tokens may be greater or leſſer, ſo ſhall the things which they betoken bee judged in like rate, either more, or leſſer.</p>
                  <p>But if the urine bee pale coloured, or flax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and then lacketh contents, as it doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare leſſer obſtruction, ſo it doth ſignifie as great cruditie, as the other before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:36549:48"/>And ſo ſhall you judge of urine that is yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low or flaxen coloured. For in them it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that naturall heat doth prevail. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſuch things (I mean the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of the ground with thoſe colours) may chance (as often they doe) through vehement pain, immoderate labour, long watching, and alſo default of matter.</p>
                  <p>But ſuch urines as be higher coloured then theſe that I have named, by their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours they declare the qualities of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours which doe prevail: and alſo betoken a certain putrefaction, and cruditie in the veins.</p>
                  <p>It chanceth alſo ſometimes, that ſome ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering ſore being in ſome of the principall members, by his unnaturall heat withdraw thither the matter (even as it were by cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping) and ſo doth cauſe the urine to have no ground. And though, indeed, it is never a good token to lack the ground in a urine, yet it is leſſe to be complained of, if the colour and ſubſtance draw nigh to a mean; for in ſuch a caſe it betokeneth, that though nature be ſomewhat ſlack, yet will ſhee ſhortly gather ſtrength, ſo that there ſhall appear a ground in the urine.</p>
                  <p>Now to ſhew you the reaſon, why it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth no ground to appear in the urine: Firſt,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:36549:49"/>
in caſe of cruditie, when there wanteth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect concoction, there muſt needs want al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the contents in the urine; for they are the excrements (as you might ſay) and the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities of the third concoction. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe though concoction be perfect enough, yet may there want the contents, if there be any notable obſtruction or ſtopping of the veins, namely, ſeeing the contents are ſomewhat groſs of ſubſtance, and therefore unable to paſs, if the way be any thing ſtop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>After the ſame ſort ſhall you judge of long faſting and default of meat, and moreover of ſuch meats as are unapt to concoct. For in all ſuch caſes, there can be ingendred few or no contents.</p>
                  <p>And contrariwiſe, though nature doe work many ſuperfluities, yet if the wombe be ſo looſe that it yeeldeth many ſeges, then as the urine ſhall be the leſſer, ſo ſhall the contents be few or none: for nature then doth expel by ſege, thoſe ſuperfluities, which ſhould cauſe the contents.</p>
                  <p>And likewiſe, when there is in any part of the bodie an inflammation or exceſſive heat, which doth draw matter to it, either that any of thoſe parts are weak, unto which nature is wont to expell ſuch ſuperfluities; for in all ſuch caſes there may want the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36549:49"/>
ground, and the other contents in the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine. And as for ſome of them (I mean crudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and opilation) they may be well enough born withal, unles their continuance be long.</p>
                  <p>But now again, there is great difference touching the time of the ſickneſs in which it chanceth, for in the beginning and increaſe of ſharp Agues, if the ground be lacking, it betokeneth great weakneſſe of naturall ſtrength, which if not prevented, may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue unto the chief ſtrength of the ſickneſſe. And after ſuch an urine, there doth follow much waking and diſquietneſs, halfe mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and trouble of mind, and all thoſe ſhall bee according to the greatneſs of the Ague, either extream or mild. And ſometime it is a token that there ſhall bee a gathering ſore in ſome part of the body, namely, if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther agreeable cauſes come therewith, as a winterly diſpoſition of the aire, with an uncertain ſtate of ſickneſs, and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant alteration, and mean weakneſs of the Patients power. But in the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſickneſs, ſuch urine ought not greatly to be blamed, for then hath nature eſcaped the brunt of ſickneſs, though ſhe be yet weak. Yea, and in the chief ſtrength of ſicknes (as well as in the declination) it may ſeem no ſtrange thing, if nature (as though al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:36549:50"/>
ſhe had the over-hand) do gather her power together, and draw a little nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to her ſelf, and thereby cauſeth little or no ground to appear. But afterward when ſhee is ſomewhat refreſhed, and doth more liberally nouriſh the body, then doth ſhee ſhew forth contents in the urine. And light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the order of the contents is ſuch, that firſt there appeareth a cloud, which afterward doth gather more ſtrong and weightie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and doth become a ſwim or ſublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And laſt of all, when it hath gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a right naturall whitneſs, and due ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, then will it grow to a ground.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of difform Contents.</head>
               <p>OTher things ſhould I here ſpeak of, as touching the Judiciall of the contents, both of their ſtableneſs, that is, their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in good form, and of their due knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, being neither tattered, nor diſperſed, nor yet overmuch clodded together. But becauſe the exact judgement thereof exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the capacitie of mean wits (for whoſe ſake I have written this Book) and cannot lightly be perceived of them, but by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36549:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of a lively voice, I wil for this time overpaſs the exact and perfect declaration of them reſerving it to a place more due: And now will I briefly over-run the other things which remain to bee conſidered in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, but yet not without ſome mention of thoſe other, as occaſion commeth: and firſt thoſe difform Contents which occupie the place of the ground,<note place="margin">Difform contents.</note> and therefore take his name alſo.</p>
               <p>Of this ſort there are four principall: the firſt is in bigneſs of a ſmall fatch, and red coloured, which you may call therefore red fatches, becauſe of their likeneſs. Theſe (as witneſſeth <hi>Galen) are ingendred of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and waſting of the fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">6. Epid.</note> 
                  <hi>when the fatneſs is already melted away.</hi> But in this there is great difference, for ſometime it is only the waſting of the reins, and ſometime of the whole body: as if there appear in the urine tokens of due concoction, then is that waſt in the reins onely. But if there appear in the urine default of concoction, (namely being great) or if the patient have an Ague, then is it the waſt of the whole body, and that ſtandeth well with reaſon, that when it betokeneth the waſt of the whole body, there muſt needs appear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of concoction; for in ſuch caſe thoſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:36549:51"/>
parts which are the Inſtruments of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction are ſo weakned, that they cannot do their office. Theſe contents, by reaſon that they are groſs and heavie, therefore they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear alwaies in the bottom of the urinall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Brannie contents.</note>Other difform contents there be alſo, of which ſome are like bran, and ſome like ſcales. And of thoſe that are like bran, there is one ſort ſmaller, and another groſſer; the ſmaller ſort is like the bran of Wheat that is finely ground, and thoſe may I call fine bran. The groſſer is like bran of Barley, or of evill ground wheat, and may therefore be called groſs bran,<note place="margin">Fine bran. Groſs bran.</note> for it is thrice as big as the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Scales.</note>The third ſort which is like Scales, hath no notable thickneſſe, but onely breadth and length. Theſe three doe betoken waſte of the ſtrongeſt parts of the bodie; but yet not all alike, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> doth declare in the ſecond Book of his Prognoſticks. Howbeit, becauſe that place of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> is ſo difficult, that ſcarcely the great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men can agree thereon, I will not now meddle therewith, but will write <hi>Actuari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> mind of thoſe three.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fine bran.</note>
                  <hi>When the Ague</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is grounded in the bottome of the veins, then there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſuch fine bran.</hi> Howbeit, ſometimes
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36549:51"/>
it is a token of the onely grief of the bladder being ſcabbed, as witneſſeth <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> 4. <hi>Aphor.</hi> 77. But then hath the Patient no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, and again, there doth appear tokens of concoction in the urine. But when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the whole body, this is the cauſe thereof; The Ague getting power and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing unto the hard parts of the body (as in thoſe Agues which are called Fevers hec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike) then in the ſtriving between thoſe parts and the Ague, the Ague having the maſterie, doth by his violence raiſe of ſuch brannie ſcurffe. For the nature of fire (whoſe operation the Ague hath) is to work accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the matter is that it findeth, either to melt it, if it be a liquid and unctuous thing, either elſe to ſcale it and fret it, if it be hard and unpliant: and the harder that the matter is, the greater ſcales it fretteth off; which thing you may ſee by daily experience, how fire melteth wax and tallow, and ſuch like, turning them into liquids: whereas of iron and of other metals,<note place="margin">Scales.</note> it maketh ſcales and not liquor.</p>
               <p>But when the Ague hath attained and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſet, not onely the ſubſtance of the veins, but alſo the ſtrong parts of the body, and doth melt and waſte them, then doth there appear in the urine, ſcales, broad
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36549:52"/>
and thin, which you ſhall know to come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the whole body (as I ſaid of the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) if the Pacient have an Ague, or the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appear default of concoction in the urine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> elſe if theſe two be abſent, it may come o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the bliſtering of the bladder, as <hi>Hippocrate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> writeth 4. <hi>Aphor.</hi> 81. and namely, if ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be in the urine an evill ſavour withall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Groſs bran.</note>Now to ſpeak of the great and groſſe bran, which as it is much greater then the other, ſo doth it declare a greater ſtrength of the Ague, and that in the whole body, and all the parts of it, enflaming and burning the whole ſubſtance thereof, and therefore is it not only the worſt of them all, but is nigh unto a deadly ſign,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and that either by the waſte and conſuming of the great and ſtrongeſt parts of the body, or elſe by the burning or drying up of the bloud. Which two things you may diſcern aſunder by the colour of them. For if they be red, then come they of the burning of the bloud; but if they be white, then come they of the waſt of the ſtrongeſt parts of the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hippoc.</hi> 7. <hi>Aphor.</hi> 31.</note>Of this kind of contents ſpeaketh <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> ſaying: <hi>In whatſoever Agues there doth appear grounds like unto groſſe bran, it is a token that the ſickneſs ſhall continue long.</hi> Which ſaying, <hi>Galen</hi> doth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36549:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſo to be true, <hi>If the Patient have ſufficient ſtrength to continue with ſuch ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, elſe it may be a ſign rather of ſhort life, then of long ſickneſs.</hi> For as that token is commonly deadly, ſo thoſe few that doe eſcape, do recover hardly, and not without the long ſufferance of the violence of that cruell Ague.</p>
               <p>Now as touching the foreknowledge of it, whether the patient may endure with it or no, that ſhall you gather of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, order, and ſtableneſs or unſtableneſs of it. For if they be many in number, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to worſe and worſe, then it is an evill and mortall ſign, and doth declare that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is wearied and doth quite faint thorow the waſte and decay of the whole conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body: But contrariwiſe, if they appear few, and do alter continually unto leſſe evill tokens, then is there good hope of health. And this ſhall ſuffice as touching theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ragged ſcraps.</note>Now to ſpeak of the reſt, of the ragged ſcraps, hairs, and other like: Firſt you ſhall underſtand, that ſometime a good ground is coupled with certain evill and unconcted fragments of all ſorts of humours, for ſometime there appeareth with the contents certain ragged ſcraps, enclining
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:36549:53"/>
in colour toward a yellow, or a white, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> elſe ſome ſuch like, if thoſe appear in gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quantitie, they declare the matter to be ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unconcoct, and that the humour (who ſcraps they are) doth abound in the depth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the body, and is as duſt or burned, but if the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bee few, then declare they the malice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the humour to be milder, and that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of evill meats doth cauſe them, the great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſuch ragged ſcraps are, the leſſer adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of humours they declare to be in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> veins, and the leſſer they be, the greater he they do betoken. For the cauſe of ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ragged ſcraps is exceſſive heat, which do turn thoſe humors into a thickneſs, and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were a bony nature, by reaſon that they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remained long in certain veins, and we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neither diſſolved, nor extenuated, nor ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quickly expelled by urine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hairs.</note>Beſides theſe there are hairs of ſundr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lengths, ſome an inch, and ſome an handfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> long, ſome longer, and ſome ſhorter; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe are in colour whitely, and do betoke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grief of the reins. Theſe are ingendred in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> water-pipes, which go from the reins t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the bladder, ſo that as long as thoſe water-pipes are in length, ſo long may thoſe hair alſo be, which are a groſs and baked humor wrought in form of a hair.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:36549:53"/>Of thoſe ſpeaketh <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> ſaying;<note place="margin">4. Aph. 76.</note> 
                  <hi>In whoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine ſoever there doth appear little peeces of fleſh, either as it were hairs, thoſe ſame come from the reins, namely, if the urine be thick.</hi> Howbeit theſe are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeen in ſuch mens urines as feel no grief in the reines, but only have fed ſome continuing ſpace on flegmatick meats, which will prepare matter to ſuch diſeaſes, as they do alſo to many other griefs, of which to ſpeak in this place it is meet.</p>
               <p>But to go on with this thing that wee have in hand, beſide ſuch ragged ſcraps and hairs (as I have ſpoken of) there appear ſometimes in the ground of the urine, and alſo diſ-parkled abroad in the urine it ſelf, ſundry and divers kinds of motes (as it were) which do declare that there is grief diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſundry parts of the body.<note place="margin">Motes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The places of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents. The loweſt region.</note>And this now may ſuffice, as touching contents of every kind: Therefore now will I a little repeat out of <hi>Actuarius</hi> of the diverſitie of judgement, by the places or regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the contents.</p>
               <p>That ground which fleeteth nigh to the bottom of the urinall, being in other points alſo good and mild, doth betoken no ſtrange thing. But if it be unconcoct and deformed it betokeneth default in nature. And if his,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36549:54"/>
parts be diſparkled aſunder, it betokene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a dimneſs in nature, which doth not reſt the rebellion of noyſome humors, ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſuch caſe there appeareth need both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> long time, and alſo more ſtrength to over<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come that evill. But as it is commendable that the ground fleet nigh the bottome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the urinall, ſo is it diſcommendable if it lye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> flat on the bottome of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The middle region.</note>Now as touching the ſwim or ſublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if it be good in colour and other waies, then doth it differ only in place from a right ground: and that cometh of an unnaturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineſs, which maketh it to be ſo light, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o fleet above his due place, but if his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and other like points bee evill, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth it betoken leſſe evill, then if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in the right place of the ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The regio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now as touching the third and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gion, which is the place of the clouds. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e appear a light and thin cloud, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th no ſmall grief of the head. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fference is there in the clouds, the that they be in colour and ſubſtance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther they differ from a right good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urall Content. And therefore need <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng time to return thereunto. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y wayes, the worſe that they are in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſubſtance, the leſs they are to be
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:36549:54"/>
blamed, by reaſon of their place, which is ſo much diſtant from the naturall place of Contents. For this is a generall rule: The lower that good contents fleet in the urine, (excepting alwaies ſuch as cleave to the hard bottom) the better they are. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wayes of evill contents and ſuch like, the higher they fleet, the leſſe evill they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the regions, to the parts of man.</note>Now to make an end of this. You ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a certain proportion that is between the parts of the urine, and the parts of mans body. The higheſt part of the urine doth betoken, the higheſt part of the body, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the head, and ſuch other neer unto it. The middle region of the urine doth repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the middle parts of man, as the breaſt, the bowels, and the parts about them. The hether region of the urine doth purport the loweſt parts of man, from the bowels downward. And if you mark well this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, you may the eaſier judge the griefs of the parts of man.</p>
               <p>For when the contents which in colour and ſubſtance are naturall, and yet by the abundance of windineſs be lift up to the higher part of the urine, it declareth ſome great pain to be in the head. And in like manner, when the ſwim or ſublimation
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36549:55"/>
doth declare grief, that grief muſt be lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to be in the middlemoſt parts of man (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I ſaid before) and ſo of the other.</p>
               <p>Again, as this proportion between th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regions of urine, and the parts of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy doth declare that place in certain heigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo doth it in breadth alſo by like proportion if you doe duly mark the ſide, unto whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the contents do decline.</p>
               <p>And if you mark wel what I have ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you may perceive the only cauſe of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch griefs, when the contents is only di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ordered in place, cometh of an unnatura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> windines, but yet commonly annexed wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> phlegmatick and unconcocted matter.</p>
               <p>And as the windineſs doth cauſe diſord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the contents, ſo it cauſeth alſo anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kind of things not to be neglected in urine and that is bubbles:<note place="margin">Bubbles.</note> which ſometimes flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the ring or garland onely, and ſometime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the middeſt of the urine onely, and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> times doe cover the whole face of the urin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The Bubbles which ſtand round abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over the garland only, and continue withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parting, if they he of the ſame colour th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the urine is, they declare great pain to be it the head, and that in all parts of the head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if the Bubbles joyn together without part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But and if they occupie only the one
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:36549:55"/>
half of the garland, then is that pain in the one half of the head. And ſo forth may you judge by like proportion.</p>
               <p>But if they doe part in ſundry places, and joyn not all together, it is a token that the pain is the leſſer, and cometh of a weaker cauſe. The more yellower that their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour is, the greater they declare the pain in the head to be. If they be white, or rather whitiſh, and ſtand about in the compaſſe of the garland, they betoken little pain or none. And if the urine bee thin withall, they betoken weakneſs of naturall heat, or elſe the opilation and ſtopping of the reins, namely, if there appear no ground in the urine. This doth <hi>Hippocrates</hi> witneſs,<note place="margin">7. Aph. 14.</note> ſaying; <hi>When in the urine there ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth bubbles, they betoken grief in the reins:</hi> And alſo that it ſhall long continue. The reaſon of the long continuance (as <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Philotheus</hi> doe both declare) is, becauſe that the grief commeth of cold and tough phlegmatick matter, which always is long before it may overcome.<note place="margin">Lib. 28. c. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>that that urine is evil, which is ful of bubbles and thick,</hi> in which if the ground be white, it is a token that there ſhal be grief either about the joynts, or elſe about the bowels. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, yet ſometimes the bubbles are not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36549:56"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:36549:56"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:36549:57"/>
an evill token, but contrariwiſe, a good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of concoction, and declare that nature doth now apply her ſelf wholy unto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction. And this do the Bubbles ſignifie, when they appear in the water, in which they were not ſeen long before. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in an Ague, we may conjecture the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of it, when we ſee bubbles to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear after that ſort; except it be ſo that they appeared in the urine at the beginning of the ſickneſs, and hath ſo continued ſtill: For then they declare grievous pain to be in the head, yea and that dangerous, if the urine alſo be thin in ſubſtance. But if the ſubſtance of the urine be thick, then the bubbles are not ſo evill a ſign, neither declare ſo greivou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> danger.</p>
               <p>Sometimes in ſtead of Bubbles which doe not appear when they ſhould, it ſufficet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that there appear a groſs ſome (as it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeen to riſe upon wine) and it doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token even the ſame thing that the Bubble do,<note place="margin">Fome.</note> eſpecially in the declination of the Ague of which I ſpake a little before.</p>
               <p>Theſe Bubbles do appear very thick aboue the garland, in the urine of him that hath the iſſue of ſeed, or waſt of nature. Sometime alſo there are ſeen in the Bubbles certain ſmall ſcrapps (as you would ſay) much like
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:36549:57"/>
hairs in groſsneſs, and of ſuch length ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time that they reach from the one ſide of the bubble unto the other, and ſometimes lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſometimes ſhorter, which things may come either of the waſting of the reins, or elſe of the ſhedding of nature.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of the generation of bubbles, and alſo of the diſperſing and elevation of the contents, is an unnaturall windineſs. Of which, as there are divers kindes much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering aſunder, partly in multitude, partly in ſubſtance, and partly alſo in quality, ſo doth the bubbles engendred of them diverſly varie, according unto thoſe differences, whether they be ſole and ſeverall, or joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many knit together. But windineſs if it be groſſe, then doth it puffe up ſuch Bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; and if it be ſubtile, then doth it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther work a diſperſion in the contents, and is not able nor meet to cauſe Bubbles. And hereby may you know the qualitie of the windineſs, and likewiſe alſo the quantitie. For there appeareth leſſe quantitie of windi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to bee where the contents onely are diſperſed, then where ſuch Bubbles be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred.</p>
               <p>Now as touching the other qualities of it, as heat and cold (which are the chief quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties indeed, and moſt active) you may judge
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:36549:58"/>
them by the colour of the bubbles. For as pale colour, and other low colours declare coldnes of that windineſs, ſo high colours enclining toward yellow or higher, be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain tokens of heat.</p>
               <p>Bubbles that are ſmall, and thick knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the garland of the urine, doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token a groſſe windineſs, whoſe cauſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be vanquiſhed; for the groſsneſs and toughneſſe that is in them, will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to ſwell great, and that cauſeth them to be ſo ſmall. And contrariwiſe, the greater that the bubbles be, and the more bouled, the more they declare that windines that cauſeth them to be ſevered from tough matter. Moreover, the colder that ſuch windineſs is, the leſſer grief is felt of them.</p>
               <p>Bubbles in the urine of old men, namely being great and large, doe betoken cold wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dineſſe, but ſometime ſuch bubbles are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſign of rheum diſtilling from the head int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the lights, eſpecially if the Patient at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> entring of Summer were very hot, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> did drink much, which matter, the head be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing dryed, did draw unto him, and did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill again part of it down into the lights whereof commeth a cough, and part of it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the womb, which thereby is moved to laxe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:36549:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the Garland and other like things.</head>
               <p>AS I have compendiouſly, and yet not very ſlightly ſpoken of thoſe former parts, to bee conſidered in urine, ſo will I briefly ſpeak of a few more, which may not well be omitted, and ſo make an end of the Judiciall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note>Firſt, therefore in the over-part of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, round about the edge of the urine there appeareth a garland, circle, or ring, which doth there appear, by reaſon that the higher part of the urine being thinner than the reſt, and more ſubtiller, and therefore doth not only more ſooner alter, but doth more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er declare the alteration. Howbeit ſometime there doth appear no ring at all; and that is when the colour of the urine, and of it is all one, by reaſon of the great force of the cauſe which altereth the urine, but yet ſo that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth match that humour, and is neither overcome by it, neither yet hath overcome it. For if nature have plainly either got the victorie, or loſt it, then is there another co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour in the garland, then is in the reſt of the urine.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:36549:59"/>Now if the colour of the urine be evill, and the colour of the garland better, it is a token of health. As if the colour of the urine bee yellow, red, or crimſon, or any ſuch like, and the colour of the garland be white, or whitely, it is a token full of good hope; but when the colour of the whole u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine is evill, and the colour of the garland worſer yet, then is it an evill ſign. As when the colour of the urine is green or purple, and the garland worſe coloured, then is it a plain token that nature is overcome, and that the evill humours have gotten the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand.</p>
               <p>Of theſe more particularly doth <hi>Egidius</hi> treat, but yet not more truly nor more ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, his words are theſe: <hi>If the circle of the urine be thick and waterie, it is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that the hinder part of the head is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with phlegmatick matter; but if it be purple-coloured and thick, then is the forepart of the head overcharged with blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A pale and a thin circle declareth the left ſide of the head to be troubled with me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy matter; but if it be red and thin, it betokeneth choler to abound in the right part of the head.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Leddy or aſh-colour.</note>A Leadie or Aſh coloured circle, doth ſignifie the falling Evill, through the great grief of the brain.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:36549:59"/>And further declareth that ſuch grief ſhall proceed by the ſinnews into the other parts of the body. But if after ſuch a leadie colour there follow a reddſh colour, that is a good token; for then doth nature gather ſtrength again, and the powers of the brain reviveth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Green.</note>If the colour of the garland be green, and the Patient have a burning Ague, it is to be feared, leaſt that the abundance of choler ſhall cauſe a Phrenſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Black.</note>Black colour in the circle doth ſometime betoken mortification, and ſometime only extream heat. But theſe ſhall you diſtinct (as I ſaid before of the urine it ſelf) by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the colours. For if green colour went before, then doth the black betoken aduſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on through heat, but if his colour laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was aſh-colour, then is it a token of death, comming through the dominion of cold. And thus much as touching the colours may ſuffice for this time.<note place="margin">Quivering in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes alſo you ſhall perceive a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and trembling in the garland, and that declareth grief in the back bone. And thus many tokens be taken of the circle or garland.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fattineſs.</note>Sometimes there will appear fleeting on the urine, certaine ſcum or fattineſs, ſometimes like drops of oyle, and ſometime
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:36549:60"/>
like a thin ſpiders web, and theſe both doe betoken the melting of the fat within the body, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> witneſſeth in his Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks,<note place="margin">7 Aph. 30.</note> howbeit in his <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> he doth aſſign it as a token of the grief of the reins peculiarly, ſaying; <hi>In whole urine there fleeteth fattineſs, and that much at once, they have pain in the reins, but ſhall not long endure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> doth <hi>Galen</hi> underſtand ſo to be true, if that fattineſs appear quickly and much at once; elſe if it come by little and little with longer continuance, ſo doth it not betoken waſt only of the fat about the reins, but rather throughout the whole body, which ſign yet is not alway evil, except it continue long; for if it continue but a little while, it declareth no great evill.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Stinking ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne.</note>Now to goe forth with other ſigns; If the urine have a ſtinking ſavour, it is ever an evill ſign, for it doth betoken ſome putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction more or leſſe; as of the bladder one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by ſome bliſter or ſore in it: and that moſt certainly, when the ſtinch is very great, and there appeareth alſo ſcales in the urine, and matter. But if there be matter in the urine, and the ſtinking ſavour but mean, then doth it declare the ſore to be in ſome other part of the body. But this ever is
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:36549:60"/>
true, that matter in urine is a token of a ſore. And if in continuance of time the matter and ſtinch doe abate, it is a good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but if the other continue or increaſe, it is an evill ſign. If the urine doe ſtinke, and there appear no matter in it, then is it a token of ſome mortifying. For if there be in the urine mean tokens of concoction, then is the mortification in ſome one part of the body; but if the other ſigns in the urine be evill, then is that mortification rather of the whole body, then of any one part of it.</p>
               <p>And thus have I over-run briefly the chief things to be conſidered in urine, which (I ſay) are appertaining or annexed to the urine it ſelf. Howbeit two other things there are, which though they be more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then theſe other, yet may they be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed no more then the other: that is to ſay, blood coming forth with the urine, and gravell expelled therewith alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Blood.</note>Blood coming forth with urine, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ſome ſore to be in the reins or blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> writeth in his <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms</hi>) or elſe ſome vein to be broken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the reins, namely if it come ſuddenly, and without manifeſt cauſe. Howbeit, as <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Oribaſius,</hi> and divers others do declare, and reaſon alſo with experience doth conſent,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:36549:61"/>
there may appear blood in the urine alſo, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that there be ſuch a ſore in the liver, or in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhaft. But in any of theſe caſes, the pain fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the place and part, will utter from whence the blood commeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gravell.</note>Now to ſpeak of gravell: <hi>Hypocrates</hi> ſaith, <hi>In whoſe urine there appeareth grave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the bottome, they have the ſtone in the bladder, or elſe in the reins,</hi> as <hi>Galen</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; but commonly if the ſtone be in the reins, the gravell will be red, as <hi>Hypocrate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> declareth in his ſixt Book of his <hi>Epidemies,</hi> And thus now will I make an end of the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial of urine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the Commodities and Medicines of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
               <p>THe greateſt commodity of urine is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared: that is, That it doth declare unto man, the manifold diſeaſes which happen unto him; and thereby doth not only give him knowledge of the cauſe, and ſo conſequently of the cure of the ſame, but alſo warneth him before of the grief to come, whereby he may take an occaſion to eſchew it, if he will be diligent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:36549:61"/>Now as this is the greateſt commoditie of urin, ſo it hath many other as well in uſe of medicine as other waies, of which I will write ſome, though not all. And firſt out of <hi>Plinie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plinie.</note> which reciteth ſtrange operations of the urine of a Hedge-hog, and of a Beaſt that the <hi>Greeks</hi> call <hi>Leontophon,</hi> and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over of the Beaſt <hi>Lynx,</hi> which I omit now with many other: but this will I not omit,<note place="margin">Urine of man.</note> that <hi>Hoſthanes</hi> ſaith: <hi>That if a man let his own urine drop upon his feet in the morning, it is good againſt all evill.</hi> And that it is good for the gout, we may perceive by Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, which never have the gout, by reaſon that their feet are ſo often waſhed with it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Oſtrich u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</note>The ſame <hi>Plinie</hi> writeth, <hi>That the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine of an Oſtrich, will do away blots and moles of Inke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo that if Urine be tempered with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of like quantitie, and ſo powred at the roots of the trees, it will both nouriſh them (as many men ſay) and alſo drive all noyance from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bees.</note>The urine alſo of men or oxen, tempered with hony, and given to Bees, will cure them that are poyſoned with the flower of the Cormier or Cornoiller tree.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Beans.</note>And likewiſe if Beans be ſteeped in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:36549:62"/>
and water three daies before they bee ſowed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> Stinging of Adders, &amp;c.</note> ſome judge that they will increaſe exceedingly. <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> ſaith, <hi>That a mans own urine is good to be drunk for ſtinging of Adders, and againſt poiſon, and alſo againſt the dropſie when it doth begin: And for the ſtinging of the ſea-Adders, of ſcorpions, and dragons;</hi> it is good to ſoke the ſtinged part withall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dogs u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</note>The urine of Dogs is good to ſoke the place that is bitten with a Dog, and to cleanſe mangineſs, and itchineſſe, if ſalt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be added thereto. And that that is old will more ſtrongly cleanſe ſcales, ſcurff, ſcabs and hot puſhes. Alſo it ſtayeth fretting ſores, namely, on the privie members. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more it ſtincheth mattering eares, if it be dropped thereinto, and if it be ſod in the rind of a Pomegranate, it expelleth worms out of the ears.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Childes urine.</note>The urine of a child under 14. yeers of age doth cure the toughneſs of breath, if it bee drunken. If it be ſod in a brazen veſſell with honey, it healeth creythes, and alſo the web and the tey in the eie. There is made of it and copper, good ſoulder for gold.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dregs of urine.</note>The dregs of urine is good for Saint <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonies</hi> evill, if it be nointed thereon, ſo that (as <hi>Galen</hi> doth wiſely add) the ſore be coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36549:62"/>
firſt with ſome other thing, and bee not burning. If it be heated with oyle of privet, and laid to the womb of a woman, it will aſſwage the grief of the mother, and cureth alſo the riſing of the ſame. It cleanſeth the eie-lids, and the creythes in the eyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Oxe ſtale.</note>Oxe ſtale being tempered with myrrh, and dropped into ſore eares, healeth the pain of them. The urine of a wild Bore,<note place="margin">Wild bore.</note> is of the ſame vertue if it be kept (as <hi>Sextus Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicus</hi> writeth) in a glaſſe, and dropped warm into them, but it hath a more peculiar property in breaking of the ſtone, and to expell the ſame, if it be drunke.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Goats urine</note>Goats urine drunke every day, with Spikenard, and three ounces of water, is good for the dropſie, for it expelleth urine by the ſege, and it cureth pain of the ears, if it be dropped into them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aſſe piſſe.</note>Aſſe piſſe (as it is written) is good for the grief of the reins, if it be drunke.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mules ſtale.</note>Mules ſtale (as <hi>Paulus Aegineta</hi> ſaith) is good to heal pain in the joynts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Camels and goats ſtale.</note>The ſtale of Camels and Goats alſo doth provoke ſege, and therefore is good for them that have the dropſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sextus Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicus.</note>
                  <hi>Sextus Platonicus</hi> ſaith, That Goats u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine (if it be drunke) doth provoke womans terms, and cureth pain in the eares being
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:36549:63"/>
droped into them,<note place="margin">Paulus Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineta.</note> and being mixed with mulſet wine, and ſo dropped into the ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it draweth out matter, if there be any.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Wild Bore.</note>The urine of the wild Bore with mulſe vineger, is good for the falling evill, if it be drunke.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dogs piſſe.</note>A Dogs piſs tempered with duſt, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in wool, will heal corns marveilouſly, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſtroy warts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Childes urine.</note>A childs urine will heal the ſtinging of Bee, Waſpe and Hornet, if the place be waſhed therewith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mans urine.</note>A mans urine will cleanſe the freckle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſpots in the face. And if a woman ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be delivered of the after burden, let he drinke mans urine, and ſhe ſhall be delive<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red ſtraight.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Collumella.</note>
                  <hi>Collumella</hi> ſaith, that the beſt dunging f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yong ſhots of trees, is mans urine, namely which hath ſtood half a yeer. For if yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> water vines or apple-trees with it, there no dung that will cauſe ſo much fruit as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will doe:<note place="margin">Sheeps urin</note> and not only that, but it cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo the ſavour and the taſte both of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and of the wine, to be much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Conſtantinus Affricanus.</note>
                  <hi>Conſtantinus Affricanus</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of a Sheep, or an Oxe, with ſome hot oil is good for the grief in the ears that cometh
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:36549:63"/>
of cold.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vitalis.</note> Urine (as <hi>Vitalis de Furno</hi> ſaith) fretteth, dryeth, and burneth, and is good for the grief of the ſpleen, if it be drunk, as <hi>Gentilis</hi> writeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aſſe ſtale.</note>The Urine of a male Aſſe, as the ſame <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis</hi> ſaith) <hi>tempered with</hi> Nardus <hi>doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and preſerve hair.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">M. <hi>Virgilius</hi>
                  </note>And as ſome ſay (by the writing of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus Virgilius) <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine is of no ſmal nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for divers folk in the time of dearth, have been preſerved by the onely uſe, and drinking of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Marcellus.</note>Alſo <hi>Marcellus</hi> the Practitioner, in the 27. Chapter doth witneſſe; <hi>That the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine of a man is good for divers diſeaſes of the wombe and bowels, and namely for the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, becauſe that partly with provoking of vomit, and partly by occaſion of ſeges, it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth ſtrongly all noyſome humours, and for the ſame cauſe doth common Practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners keep it ſtill in daily uſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ldericus Huttenus.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lderick Hutten</hi> alſo witneſſeth, <hi>That he did drive away the Ague above</hi> 8. <hi>times with the only drinking of his own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, at the beginning of his ſickneſs.</hi> And many ſtill doe uſe the ſame practiſe, and it proveth well.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Marſilius Ficinus</hi> writeth that <hi>Many men doe uſe to drink urine for the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marſilius Ficinus.</note>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:36549:64"/>
which thing did <hi>Galen</hi> write long before him, and alſo <hi>Paulus Aegineta;</hi> and doe teſtifie alſo, that it preſerved them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dranke it: at the leaſt way as they thought</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Galen.</note>All urine (as <hi>Galen</hi> writeth) is hot i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vertue, and ſharp (as ſaith <hi>Aegineta</hi>) how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, it differeth according to them that mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it. For the hotter they are that make it, the hotter is it alſo, and likewiſe the colder u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine cometh of a colder body.</p>
               <p>Mens urine is the weakeſt of all othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> except tame barrow hoggs; for they in ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many points agree with man, but the urin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of wild Bores is ſtronger.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mans urine</note>Mens urine is of as ſtrong cleanſing vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as any thing elſe, and therefore doe Fulle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſe it to ſcoure and cleanſe their cloth. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in cure of griefs alſo for the ſame reaſon it is uſed to ſoke, and waſh maungineſs, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcabbedneſs, and running ſores that are ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of corruption and filth, and ſpecially if they have in them putrified matter, and for ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſores on the privie members it is good, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for mattering eares, and for ſcales and ſcurf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if the head be waſhed in it.</p>
               <p>I have healed with it many times ſores on the toes, namely, which came of bruiſes, and were without inflammation, and that in ſervants and husbandmen, which had a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:36549:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
journey to goe, and no Phyſitian with them, bidding them to wet a ſmall clout with it, and to put into the ſores, and then to bind a cloth about it, and as often as they liſted to make water, to let it fall on their ſore toes, and not to take the cloth away till it were quite whole.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſocola</note>That medicine which is made of childes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, called of ſome men in Greek, <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cola</hi> (that is to ſay, gold ſoulder) becauſe men uſe to ſoulder gold. This (I ſay) is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good for ſores that are hard to heal. For this medicine doe I uſe for the chiefeſt, mixing it with ſuch other things, as are good for ſuch like ſores:</p>
               <p>In the time of Peſtilence in <hi>Syria,</hi> many did drinke Childrens urine and mens alſo, and thought that they were preſerved by it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Alchumiſts.</note>Of urine alſo, do Alchumyſts make divers things, as ſalt, and other things moe.</p>
               <p>And many other commodities there bee of urine, as for waſhing and ſcouring, and other like, which for briefneſs I over-paſſe, and the rather, becauſe they are commonly known of all folk.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:36549:65"/>
                  <head>Of the Diſeaſes touching <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rines, and the Remedies for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>NOw to come to that I promiſed, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the griefs which hinder urine, or expell it diſorderly, either in time oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then is meet, or in qualitie, with other faſhions then is agreeable to it, or like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſorts, I will briefly write, not intending to teach the art of curing them, (which would require a longer Treatiſe, and a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er place) but onely to name certain of the moſt common diſeaſes, and to ſet after them ſuch ſimple and uncompound medicines on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which cure thoſe griefs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Stopping of urine. The ſtone.</note>Firſt therefore, touching the hinderance or ſtopping of urine, it is not unknown, that one common cauſe is the ſtone, which ſometimes is in the reins, and ſometime in the bladder. I ſhewed you before, that commonly you may diſcern thoſe two aſunder, by the colour of the gravel, but the more ſure token is the grief in the ſick part.</p>
                  <p>Now for the cure of the ſame, doth theſe medicines ſerve, which follow. But as I have alwaies ſaid, you ſhal uſe them with the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of ſome learned Phyſitian; for there is great difference both of the grief, and of the medicines.</p>
                  <div type="medicine">
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:36549:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>Medicines for the ſtone, both in the Reins and Bladder.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Aſtra Bacca.</item>
                        <item>Ameos.</item>
                        <item>Angle toches ſod.</item>
                        <item>Betony.</item>
                        <item>Bryony root.</item>
                        <item>Bylgrum.</item>
                        <item>Chamamel.</item>
                        <item>Capers Bark, namely of the root.</item>
                        <item>Claret ſeed.</item>
                        <item>Clot ſeed.</item>
                        <item>Dock root.</item>
                        <item>Fenel ſeed, and root.</item>
                        <item>Goats blood.</item>
                        <item>Gladian.</item>
                        <item>Gromell.</item>
                        <item>Gum of Plumtree, and Cherry tree.</item>
                        <item>A hedge Sparrow.</item>
                        <item>Harebell.</item>
                        <item>Kneholm root and Berries.</item>
                        <item>Madder root.</item>
                        <item>High Mallows ſeed and Root.</item>
                        <item>Mugwort.</item>
                        <item>Parſeley.</item>
                        <item>Pelliter of Spain.</item>
                        <item>Pyony Berries which are black.</item>
                        <item>Radiſh.</item>
                        <item>Sampere.</item>
                        <item>S. Johns Wort.</item>
                        <item>Sperage.</item>
                        <item>Scholm.</item>
                        <item>Swines Fenell.</item>
                        <item>Sothern Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed.</item>
                        <item>Sour Almonds.</item>
                        <item>Tent-wort.</item>
                        <item>Tutſan Berries.</item>
                        <item>Water Plantine.</item>
                        <item>Winter Gilli-flower</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And beſide theſe there are divers others.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Alſo the Stone it ſelfe that came from a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:36549:66"/>
man, being braid and drunken, will breake and expell that other within him.</p>
                     <p>Beſide the ſtone, alſo it cauſeth the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine to be clean ſtopped, by reaſon of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the expulſive vertue, and ſometimes through clodds of blood, which reſt in the ſhaft. Sometimes alſo through tough and clammie humours, and ſometime through ſome ſwelling within the yard, and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes alſo, of which the declaration is too long for this place and time: but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time I intend to write of them at large, and of all other griefs of mans bodie.</p>
                     <p>But to return to this matter that is in hand. One other ſtop of urine there is, which doth not clean let it, but cauſeth it to avoid leſſer then it ſhould; and this commeth of like cauſes as that other laſt did, ſave that the cauſe is leſs, according as the ſtay of urine is, and therefore the cure in both is much like. For if it come of weakneſs of the expulſive vertue, then with the uſe of other hot meats and drinks, thoſe medicines are good which doe provoke urine, as theſe be that follow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="medicine">
                     <head>Medicines which doe provoke urine.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Anniſe-ſeed.</item>
                        <item>Ally-ſaunders.</item>
                        <item>Alkakengi.</item>
                        <item>Baſyle.</item>
                        <item>Bylgrum.</item>
                        <item>Cammock.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="97" facs="tcp:36549:66"/>Charlock.</item>
                        <item>Chervell.</item>
                        <item>Carawayes.</item>
                        <item>Calamus Aromati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</item>
                        <item>Cubebes.</item>
                        <item>Dictany of Candie.</item>
                        <item>Dragance.</item>
                        <item>Fumitorie.</item>
                        <item>Fatchys.</item>
                        <item>Flower delyce.</item>
                        <item>Garlike.</item>
                        <item>Ground pine.</item>
                        <item>Ginger.</item>
                        <item>Helecompane.</item>
                        <item>Honey.</item>
                        <item>Juniper and the Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</item>
                        <item>Laſe ſaverie.</item>
                        <item>Leeks. Mints.</item>
                        <item>Margerom.</item>
                        <item>Maiden hair.</item>
                        <item>Navew. Nepte.</item>
                        <item>Negella Romana.</item>
                        <item>Nettle. Pepper.</item>
                        <item>Pye Ryall.</item>
                        <item>Quinces.</item>
                        <item>Rue. Roſemary.</item>
                        <item>Rocquet.</item>
                        <item>Savine.</item>
                        <item>Sage. Saverie.</item>
                        <item>Time.</item>
                        <item>Valerion.</item>
                        <item>Wild Marjoram.</item>
                        <item>Wild Parſeley.</item>
                        <item>Wild Time.</item>
                        <item>Water Creſſes.</item>
                        <item>Woodbinde.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>with many other, and namely thoſe for the moſt part, which I named before to be good for the ſtone. But there muſt be diſcretion in the uſe of them.</p>
                     <p>Beſides thoſe, is there a diſeaſe named the Strangurie (which ſome corruptly call the Strangurion) in which Diſeaſe the urine doth continually drop forth,<note place="margin">Exceſs of urine.</note> as faſt as it cometh into the bladder. And therefore may it well be noted the firſt kinde of ſuch
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:36549:67"/>
griefs as provoke forth, and further urine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively. For that ſtrangurie theſe Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines following are noted good.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="medicine">
                     <head>Medicines for the Strangurie.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Aliſander.</item>
                        <item>Aſtra Bacca.</item>
                        <item>Brokelime.</item>
                        <item>Ceder berries.</item>
                        <item>Ceterake.</item>
                        <item>Calamus Aromati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</item>
                        <item>Gladiane.</item>
                        <item>Knot graſſe.</item>
                        <item>Kneholm.</item>
                        <item>Sperage.</item>
                        <item>Seholm.</item>
                        <item>Spatula Fetida.</item>
                        <item>Turpentine waſhed.</item>
                        <item>Wilde Fennell.</item>
                        <item>Water mints.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>But you muſt conſider (as I have often ſaid) that as the diſeaſe may come of ſundry cauſes, ſo it muſt have ſundry cures. For moſt commonly theſe are good that I have written, yet ſuch may bee the cauſe of the ſickneſs, that they may do harme, therefore take alwayes counſell of ſome learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian.</p>
                     <p>Another kinde of exceſſive making of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine cometh of the weakneſs of the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive vertue in the reins, whereby the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent piſſeth as faſt as he drinketh,<note place="margin">Flux of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine. Piſſing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. The piſs gout.</note> and that in like quantitie. This I may call the flux of urine, or piſſing evill: or after the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Greeks, the piſſe gout. For which diſeaſe it is not greatly commendable
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36549:67"/>
to ſet forth medicines with the onely bare names. Howbeit, if I doe it, I truſt no man will the rather miſuſe them, namely being warned ſo often to take no medicines with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out counſell, and ſpecially in this thing, For ſome of the Medicines muſt be received inwardly, and ſome of them emplaiſtred outwardly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="medicine">
                     <head>Medicines for the piſſing evill.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Apples.</item>
                        <item>Dates.</item>
                        <item>Elecompane.</item>
                        <item>Perys.</item>
                        <item>Myrtle Berries.</item>
                        <item>Night ſhade.</item>
                        <item>Cycory. Comferie.</item>
                        <item>Endive. Paritarie.</item>
                        <item>Penny wort. Lettis,</item>
                        <item>Lintels. Pomegranat.</item>
                        <item>Purſelane.</item>
                        <item>Vine leaves.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Other defaults there be of exceſs of urine, as of them which cannot keep their urine, and namely of children, which piſſe their beds. This diſeaſe cometh oftentimes of the diſſolution of the muſcle which ſhould keep the urine, and therefore requireth cure meet for it, and unmeet for this place, and ſuch ſhortneſſe. Wherefore for this time here I will make an end, truſting that all men will with as gentle heart receive this my writing, as I of gentleneſs have taken the pains to ſet it forth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:36549:68"/>
                  <head>Additions. Of the diverſities of Colours, and of the making of them.</head>
                  <p>BEcauſe that it is not very eaſie for every man to diſtinguiſh colours duly aſunder, I thought it good at the end of this Book, a little to touch the diſtinction and making of them, namely of ſuch as are mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this Book.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Milk white.</note>Milk white, by the name of it ſelf doth ſufficiently declare what it is; for it is the very colour of milk, though the ſubſtance need not to be ſo thick in the urine, as in the milk, for the colour muſt be underſtood ſeveral from the ſubſtance, both in this and all other colours, which thing would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, for it might elſe (as it hath often done) deceive the ſimple folk.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Horn white.</note>Horn white in like manner hath his name of the thing that it aſſimuleth moſt, for it is like the white and cleer part of a horn of a lanthorn, or ſuch like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Grey.</note>Grey is like the white part of a mans nail next unto the joynt, or like hoar hair that is not very white, for gray is ſo much darker then horn white, as horn white is darker then milk white.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:36549:68"/>
                     <note place="margin">Pale.</note>Pale colour hath a certain appearance of yellow in it, but is exceeding little. If you ſeeth a peece of the rind of Pomegranate, and then put to it thrice as much clean wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it will be a pale colour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Flaxen.</note>But if you put thereto little or no clean water, it will be flaxen coloured, that is ſomewhat more yellower then pale.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pale.</note>After it followeth pale, which is a kind of light yellow, ſomething lighter in colour then crown gold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Yellow.</note>For the colour of pure gold (as an angell or royall) is a right yellow colour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Light ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron.</note>A light ſaffron colour is, that colour that ſaffron doth make when it is ſteeped in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and laid light on any white. For if it be laid on deep, then doth it make a full ſaffron colour.<note place="margin">Saffron.</note> For that is called a ſaffron co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, which ſaffron doth die, and not that that is in the ſaffron it ſelf.<note place="margin">Red. Claret.</note> For that is very red, and is higher then claret, which is a mean colour between ſaffron and red, as if it were made of them both mixed together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Crimſon.</note>Crimſon is a dark bloody colour, well known by his own name, but is not in urine ſo light as it ſheweth in cloth. Purple,<note place="margin">Purple.</note> needeth not to be much deſcribed, being ſo commonly known, howbeit if you will ſee the making of it, mixe a dark crimſon, with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:36549:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
an orient blew, and it will be purple. And becauſe that many men be deceived in the latin name of this colour, you ſhall obſerve that it is not that which in Latin is called <hi>Purpureus color,</hi> (as moſt men think) for that is rather a crimſon, but it is called more peculiarly <hi>Purpura violacea,</hi> or <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeus color.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Blew.</note>Blew colour is the colour of the cleer Skie, or of Azure. Howbeit, in urine it is not ſo orient, but if you will mix pure white (as white lead, or pure lime) with due por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of right black (as cole duſt, or other like) then there will of theſe amount that blew, which is aſcribed to urine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Green.</note>Green is a compound colour of blew and yellow duly tempred together. And the right green have I in this Book called a ſtark green.<note place="margin">Stark green.</note> But if the yellow do exceed in it, then is it a light green; and contrariwiſe, if the blue do exceed,<note place="margin">Light green.</note> then is it a dark green: Of this green doth <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> mean, when hee doth ſay of divers herbs, that their leaves be black; and ſometime when he noteth white-lines to be in herbs, he meaneth a light green, though he other times underſtandeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a certain horineſs; of which thing in mine Herball you ſhall read more exactly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Oylie.</note>Oylie colours differ from green oylie in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:36549:69"/>
their lightneſs of hue, and thinneſs of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the urine where they appear. The light oyly is ſomewhat lighter,<note place="margin">Light.</note> (or rather) brighter and more glittering then light green,<note place="margin">Stark.</note> So is the ſtark oylie brighter then the ſtark green,<note place="margin">Dark.</note> and the dark oylie then the dark green, which all cometh through the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſubſtance in the urine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Aſh-colour.</note>Aſh-colour is darker then blew, and is made of the ſame ſort that blew is, ſave that it requireth more of the black by twofold. This is the colour of lead, which is much darker then the inner part, though indeed both are one colour, and differ onely in brightneſs and darkneſs, which ought rather to be called the hue of colours, then colour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Black.</note>Now as for black, I need not to ſpeak any whit, for as all men do know it, ſo theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry letters do ſhew it, which though of all other it be moſt deadly, yet is it ſurely of all the moſt mightie, for it overcommeth all colours, and none can change it, ſo that well it may be called the colour of death. For as death overcometh all bodies, ſo black doth damp all colours; beſide, that it is the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger and token of death, which is the end of all things, and black the end of colours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:36549:70"/>
                  <head>The Expoſition of certain VVords.</head>
                  <p>NOw for becauſe I was inforced to uſe ſome (though but few) terms in this Book, which be not wel known of the moſt ſort of men, though a great number know them well enough, by often talking with Phyſitians, I thought it good here to declare ſome certain of them, for the aid of the moſt ſimple ſort.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Ages.</head>
                     <p>Becauſe that in the judgement of urines, the differences of ages ought to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, you ſhall underſtand that the chief dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of them are four, that is to ſay, <hi>Childhood,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Childhood.</note> 
                        <hi>Youth, Manhood,</hi> and <hi>Old-age,</hi> for though there be commonly 7. Ages rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned, yet theſe be four principall, and the other three be comprehended under theſe four, childhood endureth from the hour of birth till the end of 14. yeers of age, and is of complexion hot and moiſt. At the end of 14. yeers beginneth youth,<note place="margin">Youth.</note> and laſteth till the 25. yeer, and this age of all other is in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion the moſt temperate. From 25. untill 35. yeers,<note place="margin">Manhood.</note> is the flouriſhing of manhood, but yet that manhood laſteth (though not in full freſhneſs) until 50. yeers of age, and this age is of complexion hot and dry. From 50. yeers
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:36549:70"/>
forward, is the time of age peculiarly called,<note place="margin">Age.</note> in which time mans nature is cold and dry, and not moiſt, as many doe falſely thinke.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Alterative Active q. Brightneſs.</note>Active qualities, ſee the title of qualities.</p>
                     <p>Alterative vertue, ſee in the title of vertues.</p>
                     <p>Brightneſs in urine muſt be marked for a ſeveral thing from cleerneſs. For the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe betokeneth the orientneſs and the beauty of the colour, with a certain gliſtring. And cleerneſs is referred to the ſubſtance of urine,<note place="margin">Clearneſs.</note> and is ever annexed with thinneſs of it. Yet is it a divers qualitie from thinneſs. So may an urine be cleer in ſubſtance, by the reaſon of his thinneſs, and yet not bright in colour, and not cleer in ſubſtance, but this would be well pondered, leſt this neceſſarie diſtinction, cauſe a negligent confuſion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Criticall dayes.</note>Criticall dayes be ſuch dayes, on which there is (or may be) perceived ſome certain token and great alteration in the ſick body, either to health or death, or continuance of ſickneſs. What theſe be, more at large I will hereafter (God willing) declare in a Book peculiarly, becauſe it requireth more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of words, then is meet for this place. But one thing I muſt tell you, that the ſame dayes alſo be called Judiciall,<note place="margin">Judiciall dayes.</note> but not Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, for the Indiciall daies are of another kind: but yet aſſociate to theſe other.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="106" facs="tcp:36549:71"/>
                        <note place="margin">Cruditie.</note>Cruditie is the rawneſs of the meat in the ſtomack, when the naturall operation of it cannot duely digeſt the meat which it hath received; and therefore the urine which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth default of ſuch digeſtion, is called a crude, raw, and unconcoct urine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Cupping.</note>Cupping is commonly known, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> needeth no declaration.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Cloddie u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</note>A cloddie urine is that which hath in it clods of bloud, or other crude matter, or any cluſterings of difform contents.</p>
                     <p>Dark ground is not meant of the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of colour, but rather of the ſlenderneſs of ſubſtance, ſo that it can ſcarcely bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to be any ground, by reaſon that it is ſo neer in ſhape and ſubſtance to the reſt of the urine.<note place="margin">Dulneſs.</note> Dulneſs of colour is contrary to brightneſs, ſo that when the colour lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all brightneſs, then is it clean dulled, and whatſoever thing cauſeth decay of ſuch brightneſſe, that thing dulleth urine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Divers.</note>Thoſe contents be called divers, which have neither their own right form, nor any other certain, but are altogether diſordered and out of form, rather ſeeming to be many, then to be one.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Duly knit.</note>Duly knit, is a property of due contents, when they are not tattered, ragged, nor jag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, nor flittering aſunder, nor yet are not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:36549:71"/>
ſo clammed together, as tough fleam, or any ſuch thing, but are in a moderate mean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both theſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">A gathering</note>A gathering ſore, is that ſore that is cauſed of the exceſſive recourſe of humours into any part of the body, as a bile, or any other like.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Harveſt.</note>Harveſt, ſeek times of the yeer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Judiciall dayes.</note>Judiciall daies, ſeek Criticall dayes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Inequalitie.</note>Inequalitie of ſubſtance in urine doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be the difforments and diſagreeing of the parts of it together; as when it is thin in one part, and thick in another. Howbeit, it is as well uſed for the alteration from a mean ſubſtance to thickneſſe or thinneſſe, or other wayes unnaturall. Obſtruction,<note place="margin">Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> is a ſtopping commonly of the veins, and ſuch great conduits (which convey blood or any other humour) ſo that the thing which they ſhould convey cannot freely paſs as it ought. But if the like ſtopping happen in the pores of the skin, (I mean thoſe unſenſible holes, by which ſweat paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth out) ſo that neither ſweat, nor any like excrement may paſs that wayes, then is it moſt named Oppilation. Howbeit,<note place="margin">Oppilation.</note> as theſe words be ſometimes uſed the one for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo they be applied alſo to other ſundry parts of the body; but evermore they beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:36549:72"/>
ſuch ſtopping in that part, that natures work is hindered thereby.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Principall members.</note>Principall members (as to our purpoſe now) are theſe 3. the brain, the heart, and the liver.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Paſſive. Putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>Paſſive: ſeek Qualities.</p>
                     <p>Putrefaction is commonly known to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, rotting.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Qualities.</note>Qualities active, are named heat and cold, becauſe they are more apt and able to work, then to be wrought. And contrarie waies, drineſs and moiſture are named paſſive, or ſuffering qualities, becauſe they are more ready to be altered by the working of hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and cold, then to work themſelves; howbei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> yet they doe work alſo.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The four times of ſickneſſe.</note>There be in ſickneſs four principall parts of time, to be obſerved of Phyſitians: The beginning of ſickneſs, the increaſe or aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, the ſtanding or chief force of it, and the declination or aſſwaging of it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>The beginning is, from the time that ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath overcome mans ſtrength, and brought him to lie down, till there doe appear manifeſt ſignes of concoction of the matter,<note place="margin">The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</note> whereof the diſeaſe cometh, at which time, the ſickneſs waxeth fiercer and fiercer: and while it ſo continueth, that time is called the Increaſe and augmenting
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:36549:72"/>
of ſickneſs, but when the violence of the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is at the moſt,<note place="margin">The ſtate.</note> ſo that the rage of it is at one ſtay, and neither increaſes nor decreaſes, that time is called the ſtanding, ſtay, ſtate, or chief ſtrength of the ſickneſs. And after that the furious rage of ſickneſs doth abate, and calm his cruell ſtormes, then is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the ſickneſs:<note place="margin">Declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> after which (if the Patient eſcape as very few die in the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) then followeth recovery to health a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. And theſe be the four generall or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall times of ſickneſs. Beſide theſe there be other times more particular,<note place="margin">Times of the yeer.</note> wherof how to ſpeak I need not. The diverſity of times in the yeer are duly to be obſerved, for they do much alter mans body.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Spring.</note>The Spring time increaſeth blood and bringeth all the parts of the body to a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, as nigh as it can. For it of all other times is the moſt temperate, neither exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively hot, nor cold; neither moiſt, nor dry; but of a juſt temperature, as <hi>Galen</hi> proveth abundantly in his firſt Book of Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, where he doth much blame them that name it to be hot and moiſt, which he ſaith, is of all other the moſt peſtilent ſtate of air. This Spring, after <hi>Galens</hi> minde, doth begin about the tenth day of <hi>March,</hi> and endeth about the 14. day of <hi>April,</hi> ſo
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:36549:73"/>
that it laſteth but 6. weeks, and 2. dayes. For at the riſing of the <hi>Pleiades</hi> (which is now in our time about the 24. day of <hi>Aprill</hi>) he ſaith that Summer doth begin.<note place="margin">Summer.</note> Which Summer is in complexion hot and dry, and therefore meet to increaſe choler, which in that time doth abound. The Summer laſteth 21. weeks.<note place="margin">Harveſt.</note> Harveſt doth begin after <hi>Galens</hi> minde, about the 17. day of <hi>September,</hi> and laſteth 7. weekes. The Harveſt, is dry of complexion, but neither only hot, nor only cold, but is diſtemperate in heat and cold. For in the morning and evening it is cold, and at noon it is hot. So may it not be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led juſtly (as men do name it) cold and dry. In this time doth melancholy increaſe. At the end of Harveſt, about the ſeventh day of <hi>November,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Winter.</note> doth Winter begin, which time is cold and moiſt; and therefore increaſeth flegm, which is like in complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto it. And the Winter laſteth till the 10. day of <hi>March;</hi> ſo is it in length about 17. weeks and a half, and then beginneth the Spring time again. And this is the courſe of the year, after Phyſick. Other men which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of Husbandry,<note place="margin">Another ſort of theſe times.</note> do part the yeer into 4. equall parts, giving 3. months to every time. Unto the Spring they give <hi>February, March,</hi> and <hi>April.</hi> To the Summer, <hi>May,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:36549:73"/>
June,</hi> and <hi>July.</hi> Unto Harveſt, <hi>Auguſt, September, October.</hi> And unto winter they appoint <hi>November, December,</hi> and <hi>January.</hi> Why the Phyſitians part the yeer one way, and writers of husbandry another way, at more convenient time I will declare.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Vertues. Attractive.</note>Vertues naturall are four. The firſt is, That which draweth nouriſhment into due pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that is called the attractive vertue. The ſecond,<note place="margin">Alterative.</note> is it that altereth the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into a due form to nouriſh the body, and is called the alterative vertue. The third is that vertue,<note place="margin">Retentive.</note> which keepeth in the good nouriſhment, till the alterative vertue hath duly altered it, and therefore is called the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive vertue. The fourth, is called the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue expulſive,<note place="margin">Expulſive.</note> becauſe his office is to expel thoſe ſuperfluous excrements which are left, when the other vertues have done their office duly.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36549:74"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
